<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0061">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Diary of a trip from Edinburgh to Iona, 1807</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                        <idno>Acc. 8625</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus/>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <quote>All travel has it's advantages; if the passenger visits <hi rend="underline">better</hi> countries, he may learn to <hi rend="underline">improve</hi> his own; and if fortune carries him to <hi rend="underline">worse</hi>, he may learn to <hi rend="underline">enjoy</hi> it.</quote>
                </p>

                <p>Johnson ––––– <note type="editorial">
                        <bibl type="editorial">Samuel Johnson,
                                <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0095">
                                <hi rend="italic">A Journey to the
                                    Western Islands of Scotland</hi>
                            </title>, (London: 1775)
                                <biblScope unit="page">p.322</biblScope>
                        </bibl>.</note>
                </p>
                <pb n="1"/>
                <fw>1</fw>
                <p>[Edinburgh]</p>
                <p>7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Aug.</p>
                <p>On Friday the 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of August 1807 I set out from
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0076">Edinburgh</placeName> with my friend
                        <persName ref="pe0514">Hall</persName> on the top of the <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0590">Lanark</placeName> Coach; we had previously
                    breakfasted together at his rooms, and as the morning was delightful we enjoyed
                    our ride exceedingly. There is certainly something in the beams of the morning
                    Sun, and in the coolness of the air, which is particularly invigorating to the
                    mind; and I should always desire to commence any journeys, like Obidah in <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0566">the Rambler</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <note type="editorial">A reference to the opening line of 'Obidah and the hermit;
                        an eastern story', from Samuel Johnson's periodical <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0566">
                                <hi rend="italic">The
                        Rambler</hi>
                            </title>
                        </bibl>:'Obidah, the son of Abensina, left the
                        caravansera early in the morning, and perused his journey through the plains
                        of Indostan.' <bibl type="authorial">
                            <biblScope>65</biblScope>,
                            (1750).</bibl>
                    </note> with a fine morning. We passed through 30 miles of
                    very dreary country and arrived at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0590">Lanark</placeName> about 2 o clock, which though a County town, we were
                    much disappointed to find a miserable collection of thatched houses, not so good
                    as an English village. However I do not wish <hi rend="underline">my
                        readers</hi> to infer from this, that all Scotch County Towns are equally
                    bad; <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0590">Lanark</placeName> being by far worse than
                    any town <pb n="2"/>
                    <fw>2</fw>which I have seen in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0705">Scotland</placeName>. We took our dinner at the Inn,
                    which is a very poor one. We then walked by <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1052">the
                        fine Cotton Mills</placeName> to the beautiful grounds of <persName ref="pe0512">Lady Ross</persName> at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1053">Boniton</placeName>, where owing to my kind friend
                        <persName ref="pe0513">Miss Walker</persName>, the Gardener was at
                    the pains to shew us every thing to advantage. From the <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1054">Pavilion</placeName> a little building erected on an
                    eminence, <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0592">the Corra Linn</placeName> is seen to
                    the greatest advantage. It consists rather of two falls, but we were told that
                    when the river is full, it forms but one magnificent cataract; the descent of
                    the water is near <unclear reason="illegible">80 feet</unclear>. Higher up is
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0593">the Boniton Fall</placeName> which <add place="above">is</add> extremely beautiful, it forms an excellent contrast
                    to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0592">the Cora Linn</placeName> which like a
                    boiling cauldron is all noise and agitation, while the former falls in such a
                    regular stream that you could almost fancy it artificial.</p>
                <p>The banks of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0600">the Clyde</placeName> are here
                    completely perpendicular and of immense height. In an appropriate situation
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1055">a little Cave</placeName> has, by means of
                    Gunpowder, been hollowed out of the rock, and furnished with much taste. <pb n="3"/>
                    <fw>3</fw>After admiring all the beauties of the place we were
                    regaled with delicious grapes from the hothouse and returned to our Inn to tea.
                    After walking a little about the town as the evening was fine, we retired to
                    rest at an early hour.</p>
                <p>[Hamilton]</p>
                <p>8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 15 miles</p>
                <p>On the 8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> we set out from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0590">Lanark</placeName> after breakfast and had a charming
                    walk along the banks of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0600">the Clyde</placeName>
                    to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0597">Hamilton</placeName> we stopped on our way
                    to see the fine <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0594">fall of Stone-byres</placeName>
                    which only is able to contest the palm with <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0592">the
                        Corra Linn</placeName>; I prefer the latter.</p>
                <p>We passed <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1090">
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Malsey</unclear> Castle</placeName> a sweet place of <persName ref="pe0525">Lord <sic>Hynford's</sic>
                    </persName>. The whole of the
                    road to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0597">Hamilton</placeName> a distance of 15
                    Miles is uncommonly beautiful, being newly made through Orchards and
                    plantations. We first took our dinner at the Inn and devoted the afternoon to
                    viewing the interior of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0598">the Ducal
                        palace</placeName> which is only worth visiting for the fine paintings it
                    contains. The long Gallery is adorned with many valuable pieces; <rs type="art" ref="ardb.xml#ar0076">The famous picture by Rubens of Daniel in the Lion's
                        Den</rs> did not <add place="above">at</add> all please me; The figure of
                    Daniel exactly answers to my idea of the Prodigal <pb n="4"/>
                    <fw>4</fw>Son eating husks with the Swine, when I should rather have expected an
                    angelic countenance inspired with the full confidence of divine protection. <rs type="art" ref="ardb.xml#ar0077">The portrait of the Earl of Denbigh by
                        Vandyke</rs> is life itself; and <rs type="art" ref="ardb.xml#ar0078">the
                        portrait of the famous Duchess of Hamilton</rs> (formerly Miss Gunning) is
                    the very perfection of gracefulness and beauty. The grounds though they appear
                    well laid out, are in very bad order.</p>
                <p>[Glasgow]</p>
                <p>9<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 11 Miles</p>
                <p>On the 9<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> we went to <placeName ref="Hamilton Parish Church">church at Hamilton</placeName> and set out
                    immediately after service for <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>, we digressed from the road to see the beautiful ruins
                    of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0599">Bothwell Castle</placeName> which stand in
                    the grounds of <persName ref="pe0506">Lord Douglas</persName> close to
                    the river, there is enough left to discover that it must once have been
                    magnificent; it is very tastefully surrounded with fragrant and flowering Shrubs
                    and certainly forms a most beautiful object from the modern house which is not
                    at a great distance from it. We went to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1057">the
                        Tontine</placeName> where we enjoyed our dinner exceedingly. <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> is really a very fine City, the
                    street in which <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1057">the Tontine</placeName> stands,
                    pleases <pb n="5"/>
                    <fw>5</fw>me most and there are many handsome streets that intersect it at right
                    angles, one thing remarkable is that they all terminate with some handsome
                    public building.</p>
                <p>10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On the 10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> we delivered our letter though we only
                    found one of our friends at home <persName ref="pe0521">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Black</persName> with whom we drank tea. We
                    went to the Theatre w<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> is a most elegant building
                    and had the pleasure of hearing <persName ref="pe0507">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Mountain</persName>.</p>
                <p>11<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>11<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> This day we were kindly entreated to devote to
                        <persName ref="pe0520">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Anderson</persName>, who was so obliging as to accompany us to many objects
                    of curiosity in the City, such as large manufactories all moving by the power of
                    Steam, and what struck me particularly a large house on one side the street, the
                    machinery of which was all moving by an engine on the other side; the steam
                    being convey'd under the street by means of tubes. <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1058">The Infirmary</placeName> is also a very handsome and
                    commodious building. <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1059">The old
                        Cathedral</placeName> is divided into two places of worship which are very
                    elegantly fitted up. We spent the afternoon very pleasantly with D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi>
                    Anderson.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="6"/>
                    <fw>6</fw>We were much pleased with the elegant building which is built for the
                    reception of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1060">Hunter's Museum</placeName>; it's
                    exterior has all the classic simplicity of an antique temple. It is however at
                    present too near <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1061">the old College</placeName> to
                    have a very fine effect, but we were told that some of the buildings were to be
                    moved.</p>
                <p>[Dumbarton]</p>
                <p>12<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On the 12<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> after taking an early dinner with our
                    kind friends <persName ref="pe0520">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> and
                            M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Anderson</persName> we left <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0229">Glasgow</placeName> by the <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> Coach. The view from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1062">
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Dalnotter</unclear>
                        Hill</placeName> down <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0833">the Firth of
                        Clyde</placeName> is remarkably fine. As soon as we arrived we walked
                    immediately to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0226">the Castle</placeName> which is
                    situated on a lofty rock nearly insulated. The view from the top was to us
                    rendered more interesting by a very brilliant setting sun, which we stayed on
                    the rock to admire till it sank behind the Western Hills.</p>
                <p>[Loch Lomond]</p>
                <p>13<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 17 Miles</p>
                <p>On the 13<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> We left <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> and proceeded by the side of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1063">Leven water</placeName> to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0225">Bonhill</placeName> where we saw <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1064"> the Monument of Smollet</placeName> an elegant Tuscan
                    pillar; part of the inscription has been defaced either by the <pb n="7"/>
                    <fw>7</fw>hand of time or mischief. The country now begins to assume a ruder
                    character after entering the boundary of the Highlands. From the summit of a
                    hill we were soon gratified with a view of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0223">Loch
                        Lomond</placeName> which with it's six and twenty wooded islands burst upon
                    us at once in full beauty. When we reached the Lake we were delighted with the
                    variety of it's shores which are finely cultivated and were wooded in the
                    broader part of the Lake, but are mountainous and rude, where it narrows to the
                    North. We passed <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1065">Rossdue</placeName> a
                    beautiful place belonging to <persName ref="pe0508">Sir James
                        Culquhoun</persName>, took our dinner at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0224">Luss</placeName>, and then walked on to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1066">Inveruglass</placeName> where we crossed the Lake to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1067">Dennan</placeName>, the little Inn at the foot of
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0609">Ben Lomond</placeName> which we hoped to
                    ascend in the morning; but the morn<hi rend="superscript">g.</hi> was so rainy,
                    and the summit of course so obscured with clouds that to ascend was
                    impossible.</p>
                <p>14<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The rain descended in torrents, so that we were immersed the whole day in the
                    house, which could neither afford us a <hi rend="underline">book</hi>, nor pen
                    ink and paper, never was a place so barren of amusement. It is really
                    astonishing that rational beings can<pb n="8"/>
                    <fw>8</fw>exist, (as the inhabitants of this solitude must do) in such hopeless
                    destitution and dismal inanity. As the rain ceased in the evening, and the moon
                    shone very bright, we went out in a boat on the Lake, and admired the silver
                    radiance which was thrown over it's sublime Scenery.</p>
                <p>[Ben Lomond]</p>
                <p>15<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 6 Miles</p>
                <p>The morning of the 15<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> was equally cloudy, however
                    we determined to attempt an ascent and had absolutely arrived about half way up,
                    when we became completely enveloped in Clouds and therefore thought it
                    altogether needless to continue our toilsome journey, as the view which ought to
                    have been the reward of our labours could not, in such circumstances, be
                    enjoyed. As soon as we descended, we crossed the Lake to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1066">Inveruglass</placeName>, and walked to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0222">Tarbet</placeName> through the most beautiful Scenery
                    I ever saw; the road running close to the side of the Lake and presenting the
                    traveller with one of the most sublime views in nature; the rugged <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0609">Ben</placeName> rearing it's immense sides almost
                    perpendicular from the Lake, which is perfectly embowered with it's shade, and
                    sleeps <pb n="9"/>
                    <fw>9</fw>as it were beneath it in sluggish tranquility. After so long a walk we
                    enjoyed our breakfast exceedingly though here we first met with the
                    mortification of being <hi rend="superscript">*</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">obliged</hi>
                    <note type="authorial" place="foot">
                        <hi rend="superscript">*</hi>
                        <hi rend="underline">or go without</hi>
                    </note> to eat oat Cakes I
                    entreated the Landlord to let me see the pane of Glass on which are inscribed
                        <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0536">those beautiful verses</title>
                    </bibl>
                            beginning <quote>
                        <l>"Stranger if e'er this pane of Glass perchance</l>
                                <l>"Thy roving eye should cast a casual glance</l>
                            &amp;c</quote>
                </p>
                <p>The window which was thus <hi rend="underline">hallowed</hi> by the <hi rend="underline">diamond</hi> of the poet gave light to a little room in
                    which a party of smugglers were smoking and drinking; and they were not a little
                    entertained with the attention which I appeared to bestow upon the lines, and
                    made some <hi rend="underline">sarcastic</hi> comments upon my curiosity; being
                    I suppose rather offended at my intrusion. We rested at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0222">Tarbet</placeName> some hours and walked on to
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1008">Arroquhar</placeName> to dinner, which is
                    an excellent Inn by the side of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0221">Loch
                        Long</placeName>, surrounded by some fine woods, and bearing every mark of
                    once having seen better days. It was the family seat of the Macfarlanes, before
                    their estate passed into other hands. We enjoyed much the fine Herrings &amp;
                    fresh caught trout of the Lake, and after dinner amused ourselves <pb/>
                    <fw>10</fw>with rowing about, upon the Lake by Moonlight The Scenery of
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0221">Loch Long</placeName> is particularly
                    grand, and interesting; it is closely surrounded with very high mountains upon
                    whose tops the clouds almost continually repose and the effect of all this was
                    heightened by the multitude of roaring torrents, which owing to the heavy rains
                    which had lately fallen, were rushing down their rugged sides, as if eager to
                    mix their tributary streams with the waters of the Lake.</p>
                <p>[Loch Fyne]</p>
                <p>16<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>22 <hi rend="underline">Miles</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The morning of the 16<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> was by no means propitious
                    to our journey, as the rain fell without ceasing till 2 o clock, when (as it
                    neither suited our <hi rend="underline">purse</hi> nor our <hi rend="underline">inclination</hi> to be stationary) we determined to set out as the rain had
                    a little abated; but it soon came on again after we left the Inn, and we were
                    almost wet through before we arrived at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1068">Glencroe</placeName>; but this did not prevent us from stopping to admire
                    the uncommon grandeur of the objects presented to our view. The lofty craggy
                    rocks whose tops are involved in clouds, and the comparative narrowness of the
                    pass are wonderfully sublime, and to do them justice it would ideally require
                    the <hi rend="underline">pen</hi> of <persName ref="pe0073">Johnson</persName> or the <hi rend="underline">pencil</hi> of <persName ref="pe0509">Salvator Rosa</persName>.<hi rend="superscript">*</hi>
                    <note type="editorial" place="foot">
                        <hi rend="superscript">*</hi> a
                        famous painter of rude scenery.</note> The Steep Hill <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0220">"Rest and be thankful"</placeName> rises at the end of
                    the Glen, and is so perpendicular, that <pb n="11"/>
                    <fw>11</fw>the road is obliged to make many zig zags to reach the top, from
                    whence as from a Gallery midway up the rocks you have a fine view of the whole
                    Glen; that part of the road where the seat is hollowed out, being just on the
                    edge of a tremendous precipice and protected by a parapet. The seat which is
                    made in the rock and would hold a dozen people has behind it a large stone
                    bearing upon it the words <hi rend="underline">Rest</hi> and <hi rend="underline">be thankfull</hi> inscribed in large letters, with the
                    date; The simplicity of the inscription accords exactly with the tenor of one's
                    thoughts in such a situation, and after having ascended the hill it is
                    impossible not to be thankful for a rest. After leaving <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1068">Glencroe</placeName> we soon arrived at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1069">Cairndow</placeName> by the side of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1070">Loch Fyne</placeName>, where we got a comfortable
                    dinner and a <hi rend="underline">dram</hi>, and walked on in our wet clothes,
                    after first being rowed over an arm of the Lake, to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0217">Inverary</placeName>; the road is very beautiful the
                    whole way, having on one side fine woods and the Lake on the other, the view of
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1071">Ardkinglass</placeName>
                    <persName ref="pe0510">Sir Alexander Campbell's</persName> a fine white
                    house with plantations around it; from the opposite side of the lake is
                    extremely pretty; among so much wild scenery, looking as <persName ref="pe0511">Dyer</persName> says, <quote>"Like a pearl upon an
                        Æthiop's arm"</quote>
                    <note type="editorial">A reference to John Dyer's 1726
                        topographical poem, <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0562">'Grongar Hill'</title>
                            <biblScope unit="line">l.113</biblScope>
                        </bibl>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="12"/>12 On arriving at a point opposite, you first get a view of
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0217">Inverary</placeName> which with the immense
                    woods, the fine Castle, and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0218">the hill of
                        Dunaquaich</placeName> with the tower upon it's top, form such an assemblage
                    of interesting objects, as can seldom be equalled. On a nearer approach one is
                    disappointed to find <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1072">the town of
                        Inverary</placeName>, which at a distance makes a great show, almost <hi rend="underline">a make believe</hi>, as the houses are painted a story
                    higher than they really are merely to make a pretty appearance from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0217">the Castle</placeName>. The situation of the town
                    however is certainly delightful and the shipping, as quay forms the principal
                    street, has a lively appearance. We were very happy on our arrival at the Inn to
                    take our tea and go early to bed as this was by far our longest day's
                    journey.</p>
                <p>[Inveraray]</p>
                <p>17<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The 17<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> we devoted to viewing minutely every thing
                    that was worth seeing at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0217">Inverary</placeName>,
                    we first visited the Castle with which we were highly delighted. The Hall which
                    occupies the centre of the building and takes in the whole height of the Castle
                    is really magnificent, it is surrounded with Galleries which are adorned with
                    groupes of exquisite Statuary; and the walls are graced with the arms of a
                    highland chief. <rs type="art" ref="ardb.xml#ar0079">The Tapestry with which the
                        Drawing room is hung</rs> is surprisingly beautiful; <pb n="13"/>
                    <fw>13</fw>it represents Arcadian Scenes, and with all the beauty and delicacy
                    of painting: the colours are more brilliant than any thing I ever saw, and the
                    large mirrors with which the room is adorned make it quite a fairy scene. There
                    are but few paintings at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0217">Inverary</placeName>.
                    The extensive walks which lead in every direction through the woods are kept in
                    excellent order; and there is a noble avenue of venerable beeches a mile and a
                    half in length where we were told that <persName ref="pe0515">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Lewis</persName>, who resides constantly at
                    the Castle, is seen for hours together walking in silent meditation with his
                        <q>eye in fine frenzy rolling</q>
                    <note type="editorial">
                        <bibl type="editorial">William Shakespeare, <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0565">
                                <hi rend="italic">A Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>
                            </title>
                            <biblScope unit="act">V</biblScope>.<biblScope unit="scene">i</biblScope>.<biblScope unit="line">12</biblScope>.</bibl>
                    </note>
                    and here composes his interesting romances, I shall not wonder for the future at
                    his moving descriptions of female beauty, since he has had such a divine model
                    as <persName ref="pe0516">Lady Charlotte Campbell</persName>; an
                    anecdote is related of him which certainly does credit to his talents as a Poet.
                    As he was strolling with <persName ref="pe0516">Lady
                        Charlotte</persName> through the woods, they were accosted by a crazy woman
                    to the no small terror of her Ladyship. To a poetical mind however no incident
                    is lost: and <persName ref="pe0515">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Lewis</persName> almost immediately composed that beautiful ballad <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0563">"Crazy Jane"</title>
                    </bibl>,
                    which he addressed to his fair companion on their way home. In the afternoon
                        <persName ref="pe0514">Hall</persName> got a boat and rowed about
                    upon the Lake <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1070">(Loch Fyne)</placeName> but I
                    preferred sauntering about the woods of the Castle.</p>
                <pb n="14"/>
                <fw>14</fw>
                <p>[Loch Awe]</p>
                <p>18<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 20 Miles</p>
                <p>On the 18<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> we breakfasted at <persName ref="pe0517">Colonel Graham's</persName>, to whom we had an
                    introductory letter. He is a very sensible and agreeable man, has seen a great
                    deal of the world and not without observation; as he had been quartered at
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1073">Southampton</placeName>, which was
                    discovered in the course of conversation, <hi rend="underline">we</hi> were not
                    at a loss for topics. He was so obliging as to insist on sending us a few miles
                    on our way in his chaise, which contributed to lessen our walk to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0270">Port Sonachan</placeName>, a singe house by the side
                    of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0269">Loch Awe</placeName> where we crossed the
                    Lake and walked on through beautiful woods to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1074">Taynuilt</placeName>, and Inn at the foot of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0831">Ben Cruachan</placeName>, a stupendous mountain but
                    with the finest conical top I ever saw. As it rained hard all the way from
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0269">Loch Awe</placeName> we were not a little
                    glad to reach the end of our day's journey where we dried ourselves over a peat
                    fire, got an excellent dinner and comfortable beds.</p>
                <p>[Mull]</p>
                <p>19<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 12 Miles</p>
                <p>On the 19<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> after breakfasting we set out from
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1074">Taynuilt</placeName>, and had a delightful
                    walk, as the day was a very fine one, by the side of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1075">Loch Etive</placeName>, on which stand the noble ruins
                    of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0685">Dunstaffnage Castle</placeName>. When we got
                    within a few miles from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1076">Oban</placeName> we
                    were overtaken by a man driving <add place="above">a Cart</add> in which were
                    two pretty girls, who we afterwards found were his daughters; as the day was
                    very hot and we appeared rather fatigued with our walk, he immediately stopped
                    his horse and <pb/>15 asked if we would like a ride, the offer was <hi rend="underline">too brilliant</hi> to refuse, and we jumped in with all the
                    alacrity which our fatigues had left us. One of the girls was really beautiful
                    and elegant in her dress; But she had been at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0229">Glasgow</placeName>! the other had never roved beyond her native mountains,
                    and was therefore all rude simplicity, though at the same time there was a
                    slight softness about them both, which rendered them very interesting. We soon
                    engaged them in conversation and they were very anxious to learn <add place="above">from</add> whence we came, and for what reason we were
                    walking. Though the jolting of the Cart was rather annoying I was really sorry
                    when we reached <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1076">Oban</placeName> and were
                    obliged to part with our fair companions who gave us their best wishes for our
                    voyage to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0652">Staffa</placeName>. We found upon
                    inquiry, that their father was a merchant in the town who farmed his own estate
                    in the neighbourhood, and drove out his daughters every day to the farm. We
                    found the Inn at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1076">Oban</placeName> so full that
                    we could not get a room to ourselves, and were fortunately put into the same
                    with <persName ref="pe0518">Sir J<hi rend="superscript">
                            <hi rend="underline">no</hi>
                        </hi> Gifford</persName> an English baronet
                    who was just returned from the islands, and was so kind as to interest himself
                    in our affairs, and give us every information which he thought might be of use
                    to us in our intended journey. As the wind was fair our new friend joined with
                    the landlord in advising us to take a boat for <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0729">the island of Mull</placeName> without <pb n="16"/>
                    <fw>16</fw>
                    <sic>of time</sic>; we therefore took a hasty dinner, and set off
                    before four o clock in a boat with two men for <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">Aros in Mull</placeName> which they hoped we might reach by nine o clock;
                    (a distance of 30 Miles.) As the afternoon was fine we enjoyed our sail
                    excessively and were gratified with a distant view of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0649">Colonsay</placeName> and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0639">the Paps of Jura</placeName>; we passed close by
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1077">Kerrera</placeName> and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0688">Lismore</placeName>. But we had not been on the water
                    many hours before the wind turned completely against us and it was as much as
                    the man could do to prevent our going back, they tacked about till our patience
                    was almost exhausted, and we were yet far from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0729">Mull</placeName>. To complete our mortification the men told us soon after
                    Sunset that they despaired of reaching <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">Aros</placeName> till morning when the tide would turn. The moon soon rose
                    beautifully, and improved <hi rend="underline">to my taste</hi> the grandeur of
                    the rocky coasts with which we were surrounded. The wind now sent us almost
                    directly upon <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0683">
                        <hi rend="underline">Morven</hi>
                    </placeName> a large almost insulated district of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0818">Argyleshire</placeName>, and I was almost afraid that
                    we should have had the honor of passing the night with the shades of the
                    Fingalian heroes. Though the incident would have been so romantic that I could
                    hardly have regretted it — To have passed a night on the shores of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0683">Morven</placeName> (<q>Heaven our covering, earth our
                        pillow</q>) a land so celebrated in the song of the poet, would have been
                    gratifying.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="17"/>
                    <fw>17</fw>But in the frame of mind in which we then were, this was by no means
                    desirable, and after tacking about till eleven o clock, we found ourselves
                    reduced to the alternative of passing the whole night on the Ocean in an open
                    boat, or being set ashore on the nearest point in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0729">Mull</placeName>; we preferred the latter, although
                    the place was 14 miles distant from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">Aros</placeName>. Our landing was not effected till midnight; and the men
                    directed us to a little Inn as they called it about 2 Miles off, where they
                    thought that we might get beds, and something to eat, for we were by this time
                    very hungry, owing to the short dinner we had taken, and also in some measure to
                    the keen air upon the water. Our walk lay across bogs and over rocks, for there
                    are no made roads in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0729">Mull</placeName>, and the
                    sudden transition from the extremes of hard and soft (for we sometimes sunk in
                    over the ancles) tickled my fancy so much, that I laughed the greater part of
                    the way to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1091">
                        <unclear reason="illegible">Skaile</unclear> Castle</placeName> which we found to be a miserable
                    hut. The people were all gone to bed however we called them up, and were much
                    mortified to find that they could absolutely give us nothing to eat, as they had
                    expended all their meal, and had no eggs or milk in the house. They told us <hi rend="underline">for our comfort</hi>, that they were to send for some meal
                    in the morning. They were merely able to give us blankets which were well
                    stocked with vermin, of a most voracious kind, as we discovered by the drops of
                    blood upon our faces and hands. We took off our coats and lay down between the
                    blanket, in a room where there were a woman and child in another <pb n="18"/>
                    <fw>18</fw>bed, and there was only a thin partition between us and the stable
                    and pig sty. We were really so tormented with fleas that we could not sleep and
                    as soon as it was light we were happy to leave our own inhospitable hosts and
                    set off for <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">Aros</placeName> though in a
                    violent rain.</p>
                <p>[Iona]</p>
                <p>20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 12 Miles</p>
                <p>It was a long walk of 12 Highland Miles, and we were both so much fatigued, and
                    faint from hunger and want of rest, that we thought we never should reach
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">Aros</placeName>. However we arrived there
                    soon after eleven o clock and without doubt enjoyed our breakfasts, though only
                    of Oat Cake, as much as we had ever done any meal on our lives; we got excellent
                    butter and Currant Jelly which was more than we expected in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0729">the isle of Mull</placeName>. After getting ourselves
                    pretty well dried and rested, we set out with horses and a Guide to Cross the
                    Island and ferry over to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1078">Ulva</placeName>. But
                    we were so fortunate as to meet with a boat and four rowers at the head of
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1079">Loch na keal</placeName>, which had just
                    brought <persName ref="pe0522">Lord Kinnoull</persName> from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1078">Ulva</placeName>, and was returning. As the roads were
                    execrable we discharged our horses, and had a pleasant row, as the afternoon was
                    very fine, to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1078">the little island of
                        Ulva</placeName>, where we dined at the Inn, and engaged the boat the next
                    morning for <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0652">Staffa</placeName> before we
                    retired to rest.</p>
                <p>21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
                </p>
                <p>We rose early as the morning was fine, and after breakfasting left <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1078">Ulva</placeName> in a small boat with sails, four
                    rowers, and <persName ref="pe0523">the landlord Mac Donald</persName> a
                    very intelligent fellow, who is always the Cicerone to the visitors of
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0652">Staffa</placeName>, and entertained us
                    highly with the accounts of the many voyages he had made thither.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="19"/>
                    <fw>19</fw>As the wind was in our favor we sailed first to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">Iona</placeName> 30 miles distant and in our way
                    passed by the pretty island of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1080">Inch
                        Kenneth</placeName> which is covered with the finest turf I ever saw in my
                    life. As the gale blew pretty strong, we soon reached <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">Iona</placeName> and upon our landing were taken to
                        <persName ref="pe0524">the Schoolmaster</persName>, who is the only
                    representative of those sages, who formerly dispensed in this <hi rend="underline">once</hi> illustrious island, to savage clans and roving
                    barbarians the benefits of knowledge and the blessings of religion. <persName ref="pe0524">The Schoolmaster</persName> accompanied us to the
                    ruins of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0978">the Cathedral</placeName>, which does
                    not appear to have been very large, though there is much fine carving about it.
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0977">The College</placeName> was adjoining to
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0978">the Cathedral</placeName> but <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0975">the Nunnery</placeName> is at a considerable distance.
                    We were shewn <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0976">the tombs of some kings of
                        Norway, France, Ireland and Scotland</placeName> who were sent hither in the
                    ages of superstition to be buried. And to this day the inhabitants do not allow
                    a corpse to be taken off the island, even of any one dying by accident. The
                    inhabitants are a miserable set of people and they stared at us and ran about us
                    just as I should imagine the savage inhabitants of any island in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1081">the Pacific Ocean</placeName> would have done, and
                    their habitations are I should think little superior to the huts of the
                    Hottentots. It is really mortifying to see human nature in such a state of
                    degeneracy at such a little distance too from the most civilized and indeed
                    luxurious nation in the world. About <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">Iona</placeName> I remarked a most beautiful appearance which I observed no
                    where else; The Sea which is of a great <pb n="20"/>
                    <fw>20</fw>depth, (as the shores are very abrupt), is so clear and transparent
                    that we saw to the very bottom and all the beautiful varieties of Coral and
                    seaweed with which it is covered. The effect produced by looking out of the boat
                    in passing rapidly over it is wonderful. We re-embarked and soon reached
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0652">Staffa</placeName> which is 15 miles
                    distant, <q>borne upon the wings of the wind</q> which I really think is the
                    most delightful mode of travelling and certainly the most expeditious. Though it
                    blew so hard a gale that our little boat touched the water with the sail, and we
                    were consequently more on one side than I could have wished; but I sometimes
                    trembled to think that by a sudden squall we might very easily have been upset.
                    But now all thoughts of danger and every other selfish consideration were
                    absorbed in our anxiety to see, and as we approached it in astonishment and
                    surprise at the view we now enjoyed of the greatest of the wonders of
                    nature.</p>
                <p>[Staffa]</p>
                <p>The whole of the South West side resembles a vast colonnade of regular pillars
                    supporting a domed roof. The entrance to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1082">the
                        Cave of Fingal</placeName> is grand beyond all description; and the swell of
                    the sea is always so great from the impetuosity with which it rushes to and fro,
                    that as soon as we had got fairly into the Cave, and they had fastened the boat,
                    not without much difficulty, to one of the broken pillars, we were glad to get
                        <pb n="21"/>
                    <fw>21</fw>out of it and walk upon the stumps of the pillars to the upper end of
                    the Cave from whence the view is very fine The ruins of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">Iona</placeName> form a beautiful object in
                    perspective. The water we were told was 8 fathoms deep in the Cave though to our
                    eyes it hardly looked more than as many feet from the clearness of the water.
                    The pillars which support the Cave are nearly 100 feet high above water, and the
                    roof though composed of broken pillars is almost polished from the violence with
                    which during the storms and in the winter Season the surf washes it, which
                    considering the immense height is certainly wonderful.</p>
                <p>What a fit evidence for the spirits of the Storm! As you may not remember
                        <persName ref="pe0519">Darwin</persName>'s beautiful description of
                    it, I shall give it you ––––– <quote>
                        <l>"Where round the orcades white torrents
                        roar"</l> <l>Beating with ceaseless surge the incumbent shore,</l> <l>Wide o'er
                        the deep a dusky cavern bends</l> <l>It's marble arms, and high in air
                        impends;</l> <l>Basaltic piers the pond'rous roof sustain,</l> <l>And steep
                        their massy sandals in the main;</l> <l>Round the dim walls and through the
                        whispering ailes</l> <l>Hoarse breathes the wind, the glittering water boils</l>
                        <l>Here the charmed<hi rend="superscript">*</hi>Byssus<note type="authorial">* A beautiful green sea weed which abounds at
                                <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0652">Staffa</placeName>.</note> with his
                        blooming bride</l> <l>Spreads his green sails and braves the foaming tide:</l>
                        <l>The Star of Venus gilds the twilight wave,</l> <l>"And lights her
                        votaries to the secret Cave;"</l> <pb/>22<l>Light Cupids flutter round the
                        nuptial bed</l> <l>"And each Coy Sea-maid hides her blushing
                        head."</l>
                    </quote>
                    <note type="editorial">
                        <bibl type="editorial">Erasmus
                                Darwin,<title ref="bidb.xml#bi0564">
                                <hi rend="italic">The Botanic
                                    Garden, Part II. Containing The Loves of the Plants, A Poem.
                                    With Philosophical Notes</hi>
                            </title>, 2 vols. (Lichfield:
                            1789), <biblScope unit="volume">ii</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="line">ll.349-362</biblScope>
                        </bibl>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The regularity with which the immense pentagonal pillars are disposed along the
                    sides of the Cave is really astonishing, never surely did any of the works of
                    nature more nearly resemble the finished productions of art. After going as far
                    as we could with safety in the Cave, we returned and walked along the broken
                    pillars by the South side of the Island, where the pillars appear as it were to
                    bend under the weight of the superincumbent strata being all most regularly
                    curved outwards, this alone would be a sufficient proof, that they must <hi rend="underline">once</hi> have been in a fluid state. On this side is a
                    large detached groupe of pillars in all possible positions called <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1083">Boo-shala</placeName>, which looks exactly like a
                    repository of pillars which were not wanted for the construction of the Island
                    but are lying their ready for use. We then climbed up to the top of the Island
                    upon which are some Cattle, as it is covered with very fine turf, and went to
                    that part of it which overhands the entrance of the Cave, where it is so
                    perpendicular that we were obliged to lie flat on the ground with our faces
                    partly over, that we might get a good view of this wonderfull place. From the
                    immense height the stumps of Pillars (which have at least six feet in diameter)
                    appeared like <hi rend="underline">dots</hi> in the ocean.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="23"/>
                    <fw>23</fw>From the top of the Island we enjoyed a most extensive view of the
                    boundless <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1084">Atlantic</placeName> with a great
                    many other Islands, the most striking was one of the <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1085">
                        <hi rend="underline">Treshnish</hi> Isles</placeName>
                    which from its shape is called <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1086">the Dutchman's
                        Cap</placeName>. We then returned to dinner in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1082">the Cave of Fingal</placeName> where the immense
                    stumps of pillars served us for table, Chairs &amp;c, as we had brought plenty
                    of cold provisions with us. No sovereign Prince ever had a more magnificent
                    dining room. There are some other curious Caverns in the Island which are
                    dignified with names, as <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1089">the Cormorant
                        Cave</placeName>, <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1088">The Clam
                        Shell</placeName>, and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1087">the Boat
                        Cave</placeName> which is so called from a boat having once entered it, and
                    being seen no more; These in any other situation would certainly be much
                    admired, but so near to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1082">the Cave of
                        Fingal</placeName> every thing else dwindles into insignificancy. We were so
                    fortunate as to get back to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1078">Ulva</placeName>,
                    before Sun set highly gratified with our day's excursion, the object of which
                    far exceeded our most sanguine expectations.</p>
                <p>[Mull]</p>
                <p>22<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> 12 Miles</p>
                <p>After breakfasting we ferried over from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1078">Ulva</placeName> to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0729">Mull</placeName>, and
                    had a long walk of twelve miles to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">Aros</placeName>, during which as we had no guide we unfortunately lost our
                    way among the bogs which lengthened our journey considerably. We were obliged to
                    remain at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">Aros</placeName> that night and
                    engaged a boat the next morning for <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1076">Oban</placeName>. The Evening was fine and we therefore walked about till
                    dark. <persName ref="pe0086">The Duke of Argyle</persName> and his
                    suite arrived that night at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">the
                        Laird's</placeName>, which made no small bustle in the island. –––––</p>
                <pb n="24"/>
                <fw>24</fw>
                <p>23<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Took an early breakfast and left <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0682">Aros</placeName> in a boat with 2 oars; the wind was very unfavorable, so
                    that we did not reach <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1076">Oban</placeName> till
                    five in the afternoon. This is a neat little fishing town and makes a very
                    pretty appearance at sea at a distance, on one side of the town, are the ruins
                    of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0722">Dunolly Castle</placeName> which stand on a
                    lofty rock closed to the Sea. We were very thankful to find ourselves once more
                    on dry land and no more dependent on the fickle winds.</p>
                <p> 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 24 Miles<note type="editorial">The marginal
                        date and measurement of distance suggest a further entry was to follow,
                        however the remainder of the volume is blank.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>