<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0395">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to David Skene</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                        <repository>Aberdeen University Library, Special Collections</repository>
                        <idno>MS 483</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>58-59</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>Transcribed from a volume of scribal copies of Pennant's original letters
                            to David Skene. The copies are likely the work of Alexander Thomson, who
                            on his death in 1868, bequeathed the collection to Aberdeen University
                            Library. See Colin A. McLaren, ‘Reports and surveys of archives in
                            northern Scotland’ in <hi rend="italic">Northern Scotland: A Historical
                                Journal</hi>, Volume 1 (1972), pp.115-125.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1769-11-10"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0210">David Skene</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I deferred answering your obliging favour till the receipt of the box but that
                    being still on its road I would no longer defer my thanks for the account you
                    favour me with of the Stocking Trade. Be so good in your next to give me <add place="above">the</add> number of inhabitants in <placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName>; also the price of Provisions of all sorts fowls
                    &amp;c. in your market with the number of <unclear reason="illegible">ozs.</unclear> that go to a pound in Beef, and Mutton and the like. My
                    object is accuracy in what I mean to publish. <note type="editorial">Pennant's
                        description of Aberdeen in his <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bi0004">
                                <hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland 1769</hi>
                            </title>
                            incorporates information on the price of provisions, probably provided
                            by Skene: see 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> edition (Warrington:
                            1774), <biblScope unit="page">pp.136-140</biblScope>
                        </bibl>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>To show you I have not been idle inclosed are two engravings for the next 50
                    plates the lowest fig. of the birds furnishing one with a pretence of mentioning
                    my good friend <persName ref="pe0210">Doctor Skene</persName>, <note type="editorial">See <bibl>
                            <title>
                                <hi rend="italic">British Zoology
                                    Illustrated by Plates and Brief Explanations</hi>
                            </title>
                            (Chester: 1770), <rs type="art" ref="ar0101">Plate XIX. (engravings of a
                                Little Auk and Auk)</rs>, and Pennant's note: 'I met with it in the
                            cabinet of Doctor David Skene, at Aberdeen, shot on the coast about
                            twenty miles north of that city, in the spring of the year', <biblScope unit="page">p.24</biblScope>
                        </bibl>.</note>when you have done with
                    them please to send them with my respects to <persName ref="pe0590">Sir
                        Archibald Grant</persName> that he may see I merit by my activity the loan
                    of his snake. <persName ref="pe0247">Mr. Professor Oglevie</persName> who has
                    been so kind as to promise me a box will I dare say be so good as to put the
                    snake into it. I trouble you to forward the inclosed to him.<note type="editorial">The snake is described and identified as Linneaus's <hi rend="italic">Anguis Eryx</hi> in both an appendix to the <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bi0001">
                                <hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland
                                    1769</hi>
                            </title> (Chester: 1771),
                                <biblScope>pp.281-82</biblScope>
                        </bibl>, and in Pennant's
                        'Caledonian Zoology', included in <bibl type="editorial">John Lightfoot's
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                <title ref="bi0231">Flora Scotica</title>
                            </hi>
                            (London: 1777), pp.48-49</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I will not anticipate my account of my journey after I left <placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName>, for as much as I can lug into the
                    explanation of my 50 plates, shall be given there.</p>
                <p>If anything new occurs in the natural history way let me hope for its being
                    communicated. I flatter myself I shall often have that pleasure. Let me add one
                    more trouble that of the prices of the paving granite as put on board.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am Dear Sir with <lb/>True regard <lb/>Your obliged and <lb/>most
                        obedient servant</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>

                <dateline>Nov<hi rend="superscript">r. </hi>10<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1769.
                        <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>.</dateline>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>