<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0396">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to David Skene</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                        <repository>Aberdeen University Library, Special Collections</repository>
                        <idno>MS 483</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>60-62</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>Transcribed from a volume of scribal copies of Pennant's original letters
                            to David Skene. The copies are likely the work of Alexander Thomson, who
                            on his death in 1868, bequeathed the collection to Aberdeen University
                            Library. See Colin A. McLaren, ‘Reports and surveys of archives in
                            northern Scotland’ in <hi rend="italic">Northern Scotland: A Historical
                                Journal</hi>, Volume 1 (1972), pp.115-125.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1770-01-07"/>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0210">David Skene</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <dateline>Jan. 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1770.</dateline>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Your acceptable favour of the 30<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> of Nov<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> arrived here in due time. Your account of the
                    prices of provisions &amp;c. claim my best thanks.</p>
                <p>Your fish I believe to be the Perca marina of <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bi0418">Linnaeus</title>
                    </bibl>: it agrees so exactly with one I
                    lately acquired: believe me that in general the numbers of Ray’s is a fallible
                    guide to the knowledge of fish; so if other marks agree I readily give credit
                    for a few rays more or less; and make this no objection to its being of a
                    similar species, provided it agrees in other characters.<note type="editorial">Pennant is referring to the practice of counting the number of spines or
                        rays in the fins and tails of fish as a method of identifying the
                        species.</note> Next month I hope to publish the first part of <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bi0019">my Iconical British
                        Zoology</title>
                    </bibl> of which I must beg your acceptance of a copy.
                        <persName ref="pe0014">My artist</persName> is now busy drawing your
                    mollusca &amp;c., to enable me to perform my promise of returning them in spring
                    with due interest in form of <placeName ref="pl0702">Flintshire</placeName> ones
                    &amp;c. &amp;c. I must beg the favour of you to continue your communicative
                    disposition and enrich me with the mention of your new acquisitions in
                    Zoology.</p>
                <p>I shall be in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> next month where I hope
                    to have the pleasure of hearing from you. Please to direct to me at <persName ref="pe0591">Mr. Mynotts Taylor</persName> in <placeName ref="pl1180">St.
                        James’s street</placeName>. I beg my complements to <persName ref="pe0247">Mr. Oglevie</persName>; could he find means about that time to convey his
                    new bird &amp;c to <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>, I should be
                    extremely glad.</p>
                <p>You seem desirous of knowing what I am about. Perhaps I may forfeit your opinion
                    of my sanity when I say I am going to form a universal Zoology as far as relates
                    to the first four classes; and to treat it in divisions according to the four
                    continents for example the quadrupeds, Birds, Reptiles, and fish of <placeName ref="pl0697">North America</placeName> by themselves, <placeName ref="pl0698">South America</placeName> by itself and thus, the three other
                    quarters of the globe. You must know I am very fond of Geography so can indulge
                    myself in Tracing my animals from Noah’s Ark till they had spread themselves
                    over the face of the earth; a task I fear I shall often find in a <lb/>Dignus
                    vindice nodus<note type="editorial">A Latin expression signifying a difficult
                        task that merits the undertaking.</note>
                    <lb/>But howsoever we may stumble on many conjectures at least, which may serve
                    for more able heads hereafter to build new systems on. Inclosed are <rs type="art" ref="ar0102">a few prints of the work in hand</rs> that you may
                    anticipate a little of it: I must now conclude with my best wishes and that</p>
                <closer>I am Dear Sir <lb/>Your faithful humble servant <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>