<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0398">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to David Skene</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberdeen</settlement>
                        <repository>Aberdeen University Library, Special Collections</repository>
                        <idno>MS 483</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>64-66</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                    <additional>
                        <p>Transcribed from a volume of scribal copies of Pennant's original letters
                            to David Skene. The copies are likely the work of Alexander Thomson, who
                            on his death in 1868, bequeathed the collection to Aberdeen University
                            Library. See Colin A. McLaren, ‘Reports and surveys of archives in
                            northern Scotland’ in <hi rend="italic">Northern Scotland: A Historical
                                Journal</hi>, Volume 1 (1972), pp.115-125.</p>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1770-04-07"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0210">David Skene</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Your favour was forwarded to me here after I had left <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName>. I am truly rejoiced that you have escaped so alarming a
                    complaint and sincerely hope you will never experience its return. </p>
                <p>I never yet could procure the snake but hope through your means to have an
                    opportunity of examining it.</p>
                <p>I shall this summer send you specimens of our ones and add the notices you
                    desire. The things you were so obliging to lend shall be returned with them.</p>
                <p>I am obliged to <persName ref="pe0247">Mr. Oglevie</persName> for thinking of me;
                    but should have been more happy had he wrote as he was so kind as to promise. Be
                    so good as to present my compliments to him; and let him know. It will be of
                    much use to me to be informed of the history <rs type="art" ref="ar0005">
                        <add place="above">of the picture</add> of the admirable Crichton</rs>; such
                    as In whose possession is it? In what garb? What time of life? and by whom
                    painted: as I am now Transcribing <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bi0001">my
                            Scotch Tour</title>
                    </bibl> and preparing it for the press these
                    anecdotes will be of much service to me.</p>
                <p>I have also another enquiry to trouble you about in respect to the account of
                        a woman who fasted for an extraordinary length of
                        time which I am told is preserved in the library of one of the
                        Aberdeens.<note type="editorial">The use of the plural denotes the adjacent
                        settlements of <placeName ref="pl0128">Aberdeen</placeName> to the south and
                            <placeName ref="pl0129">Old Aberdeen</placeName> to the north, the
                        latter being the site of the college.</note> I shall be much obliged to you
                    for a Transcript of it.<note type="editorial">An 'Account of the fasting Woman
                        of Rossshire' is given in <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bi0001">
                                <hi rend="italic">A Tour in Scotland 1769</hi>
                            </title> (Warrington:
                            1770), Appendix II., <biblScope unit="page">pp.248-252</biblScope>
                        </bibl>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Can you inform me where the Innes family live now; and where are the houses of
                        <placeName ref="pl1182">Innes</placeName> and <placeName ref="pl1181">Innermarkie</placeName>. <persName ref="pe0247">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Oglevie</persName> will tell you whether I passed by either of
                    them in <placeName ref="pl1141">Murray</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Lastly I must beg the favour of you to inform me how much in English measure is a
                    Boll of corn or meal.</p>
                <p>I hope by this time <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bi0019">my little work</title>
                    </bibl> has
                    reached you and that it meets your approbation. It will be finished about
                    Christmas when you shall see the sequel.</p>
                <p>I hope soon to have the pleasure of hearing you are well. Please to present my
                    best compliments and wishes to <persName ref="pe0586">Dr. Levingston</persName>
                    and <persName ref="pe0589">Dr. G. Skene</persName>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>and think me Dear Sir <lb/>your faithful and obedient <lb/>humble
                        Servant</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <dateline>April 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1770.</dateline>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>