<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0421">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Stuart to Thomas Pennant, on the plants and birds of Rannoch</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP369</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>1a-1b</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    <date when="1773-01-19"/>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName> Jan. 19<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1773 —</dateline>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I received yours of Dec<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> several days ago, but as I wrote you on the 23<hi rend="superscript">d.</hi> of that month a long letter in which the desire
                    you exprest was complied with, I was not in any hurry to trouble you with
                    another. About two hours ago however I was favoured with yours of Jan. 8<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi>, by which I was surprized to find that you had
                    not received it. I now suspect that <persName ref="pe0018">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Jackson</persName>, to whom I sent it
                    inclosed in a Cover, found it of such a size that he could not transmitt it to
                    you by Post. If he has not, I dare say he would embrace the speediest method of
                    conveying it to you another way. For the management of that affair I depended
                    entirely on his prudence.</p>
                <p>I am truly sorry that you should be thus obliged to write a second and a third
                    letter before you received any answer. Be assured however, if there is at any
                    time a delay of this kind, it must proceed from want of opportunity or some
                    unavoidable avocations, and not from any failure in the desire of being of any
                    little service to you in my power.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="underline">Astragalus Uralensis</hi>, as far as I could discover,
                    is not a native of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0751">Rannoch</placeName>. But if
                    you incline, in the new edition of your Scotch Tour,<note type="editorial">
                        Stuart's advice probably relates to revisions of the new edition of <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0004">
                                <hi rend="italic">A tour in Scotland. MDCCLXIX</hi>
                            </title>
                        </bibl>,
                        which would be published the following year, in 1774.</note> to give figures
                    of any of the other plants observed in that country, I am apt to think the <hi rend="underline">Arbutus uva ursi</hi> should be one of them, as not many
                    years ago it was here first observed to be of British growth. The berries which
                    it bears are called in the Galic language <hi rend="underline">breilleaga-nan-con</hi> i.e. dog's berries. They resemble very much those
                    of the <hi rend="underline">vaccinium vitis idæa</hi>, which the Highlanders
                    call simply <hi rend="underline">breilleaga</hi>, and reckon much more
                    wholesome. When there happened at any time to be a want of all other food, it is
                    said that these last have been frequently the salutary means of preserving
                    life.</p>
                <p>For the remarks I have sent you on your <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0001">Scotch Tour</title>, which I submitt entirely to
                        your own superior judgement to make what use of you think most proper, I
                        forgot to hint that in <biblScope unit="page">the 86<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> page</biblScope>
                    </bibl> there is a small mistake. You
                    mention there that <persName ref="pe0036">Lord Breadalbane's</persName>
                    tenants carry his coal for him "from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0094">Perth</placeName>". They have for many years past however been in the
                    practice of carrying these coals from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0295">Crieff</placeName> or some of the Coal-works south of it, but never from
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0094">Perth</placeName>.</p>
                <p>I likewise omitted in the list of birds, which I sent you in a former letter, to
                    write down the Osprey, though I saw one of them in Rannoch, and it is well known
                    to breed in this same country, and added, if I mistake not, <sic>it's</sic>
                    Galic name (<hi rend="underline">Ioluir'-uisg'</hi>) to the Sea Eagle or <hi rend="underline"> F: ossifragus</hi>
                    <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0418">Lin.</title>
                    </bibl>, a bird
                    which the Highlanders distinguish by no particular name that I know from another
                    large grey Eagle, which may possibly be the Golden one.</p>
                <p>As you are to delay the publishing of <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0026">a new ed. of your B. Zoology</title>
                    </bibl> till
                    next harvest I hope it may be in my power to add before that time to the List
                    you received of Scotch birds to come to the knowledge of more of their Galic
                    names, and be better ascertained with regard to others which I have already had.
                    Among a people, who are unaccustomed to distinguish nicely the different species
                    of animals, you may believe there must be sometimes a confusion of names.</p>
                <p>I am obliged to you with regard to the birds I sent you a description of. As you
                    inform that one of the ducks is certainly the female of <hi rend="underline">Teal</hi>, so I had little doubt, even before the receipt of your letter,
                    but the other, believed to be the female <hi rend="underline">Golden-Eye</hi>.
                    About the middle of Nov<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> I got a male of this last
                    species that was shot upon <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0104">Loch-tay</placeName>. It weighed two pounds and two drams. Upon dissecting it I
                    observed an extraordinary expansion about the middle of it's <hi rend="underline">aspera arteria</hi>, which a female shot about the end of
                    the same month wanted altogether. When the lungs were inflated with air, the
                    opening was of an oval figure, the transverse axis of which was about an inch
                    and a half long, and the lesser axis three quarters of an inch, whereas the
                    windpipe itself above and below that was not above three tenths of an inch in
                    diameter. In it's collapsed and ordinary state, the rings or <hi rend="underline">annular cartilages</hi> of this part folded upon one
                    another, like those of a hoop petticoat. What the intention of such an uncommon
                    organization may be I cannot comprehend, if it be not perhaps to assist in
                    making some extraordinary cry or noise, which from <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0418">Linnæus's</title>
                    </bibl> specifick name of <hi rend="underline">clangula</hi> I should be apt to think this duck accustomed
                    to.</p>
                <p>When in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0751">Rannoch</placeName> I got a sportsman in
                    that country engaged to send me from time to time such specimens as he could
                    procure of their most remarkable birds or other animals. About the beginning of
                    the last month he brought me the skins of two large Eagles which were shot ten
                    or twelve days before that on the carrion of a dog, for which as well as for
                    cat's flesh they discover it seems a greater fondness than for any other kind of
                    food. He lay in wait for them in a concealment he had for himself hard by the
                    dog. Though the Eagles were so excessively quick-sighted that the only tolerable
                    chance he had for killing was by shooting as soon as they alighted before they
                    had any time to look about them, yet he found that they were not frequently the
                    first in observing the prey. They commonly came in consequence of <hi rend="underline">hooded crows</hi> and other birds flocks to it. He had at
                    the same time the most convincing proof of their exquisite sense of hearing. Did
                    a raven but once croak, he might lay his account that, if there was a single
                    Eagle then in that part of the country, it would not fail to make use directly
                    of the signal. — The bill of one of these birds I had from him is two inches and
                    a half long, of a light bluish white at the base, bluish black at the point;
                    cere yellow; from the eyes to the nostrils covered only with short black
                    bristles; the back, throat, lower side of the neck, breast and belly all of a
                    deep blackish brown, with some mixture of rust colour; the crown of the head and
                    upper side of the neck of a light tawny colour; the quils, secondary feathers
                    and coverts of the wings white at the base, above of a deep blackish brown; the
                    tail thirteen inches long, with a broad band of white on it's upper part, and of
                    a blackish brown colour at the end; the thighs very gross and brawny; feet
                    covered with feathers to the very toes, measuring below the knee near four
                    inches round and just above the toes near three inches and a half; toes yellow;
                    hind claw two inches long, claw of the first fore-toe an inch and eight tenths,
                    of the second an inch and four tenths, of the third one inch; from the point of
                    the hind to that of the middle claw eight inches. — Whether this Eagle is in any
                    measure a variety of the <hi rend="underline">Ringtail Eagle</hi>
                    <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0026">B.Z.</title>
                    </bibl> or <hi rend="underline">Falco fulous</hi> of <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0418">Lin.</title>
                    </bibl> I cannot say, but I have
                    little doubt of it's being the same with the <hi rend="underline">melainætos</hi> of <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0499">Sibbald</title>
                    </bibl>, and <hi rend="underline">black Eagle</hi> of
                        <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0116">Martin</title>
                    </bibl>.
                    By the Highlanders it is called <hi rend="underline">Ioluire dhubh</hi> i.e. the
                    black eagle. In the summer it is seldom seen in the lower grounds, builds it's
                    nest often in the clefts of high rocks in the neighbourhood of Deer-forests, and
                    is one of the principal enemies of the fawn, white hare and tarmachan.</p>
                <p>The other I have got from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0751">Rannoch</placeName> is
                    the <hi rend="underline">Sea Eagle</hi> or <hi rend="underline">F:
                        ossifragus.</hi> The extent of each of it's wings from the body to the point
                    is about three feet and a half; bill from the angle of the mouth above three
                    inches long, below the nostrils an inch and a half broad; the short strong hairs
                    or bristles immediately below the bill hardly so numerous or so remarkable as in
                    the <hi rend="underline">Ringtail Eagle</hi>; the spaces between the eyes and
                    nostrils cover'd with the same; tail thirteen inches long; the legs yellow,
                    feathered on the sides and fore-part but little below the knees, but bare on the
                    hind part from the middle of the joint; middle of the thigh six inches round;
                    legs below the knee three inches and a half round; and just above the toes two
                    inches and eight tenths; length of the hind claw an inch and a half, of that of
                    the first fore-toe an inch and a half, of the second an inch and three tenths,
                    and of the third an inch and one tenth; from the point of the hind claw to that
                    of the middle fore-claw seven inches</p>
                <p>Eagles were very destructive and much more numerous in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0751">Rannoch</placeName> and the neighbouring countries a
                    few years ago than at present. The Commissioners of the annexed estates very
                    judiciously offered a crown of reward for each of these noxious birds that
                    should be killed. The consequence was that in a short space of time such numbers
                    were destroyed that the Hon<hi rend="superscript">e.</hi> board thought the
                    demands made upon them on that score too heavy. They have now therefore judged
                    it proper to reduce to three shillings and sixpence a reward, which, if they
                    meant it should have the proper effect, they ought rather to have increased in
                    proportion to the growing scarcity of these pernicious birds.</p>
                <p>In my last letter I told you that I sent word to <persName ref="pe0311">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> Campbell of Achalader</persName> to
                        <unclear reason="illegible">treat</unclear> one of the skins of the white
                    hares that were killed for her, in order to be sent to you. That same day I
                    afterwards happened to see <persName ref="pe0312">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Campbell</persName> himself, and let him know
                    that you wanted a skin of that kind should be preserved for you; upon which he
                    very readily assured me that care should be taken to keep the very best of them
                    for you. I expected therefore that it was to be sent to me in order to be
                    properly stuft. From a desire however of serving you, and some mistake in the
                    message, <persName ref="pe0312">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        Campbell</persName> sent it directly to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0076">Edin<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                    </placeName> to <persName ref="pe0022">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Ramsay</persName>'s
                    care, trusting it to him to get it stuffed and then forwarded to you. The head
                    and all the external parts were left intire. The fore-head and one of the eyes
                    had some blood about them. In other respects the fur was as well preserved and
                    as pure and white as any I have seen.</p>
                <p>I am affraid however that it must have been considerably hurt in the carriage. If
                    it has, I have hopes that a new specimen may be still procured some time this
                    winter; and if it is, I shall endeavour to get it stuft for you of the natural
                    size, and fixt in the attitude proper for drawing. <rs type="art" ref="ardb.xml#ar0038">The figure you have already given of the white hare in
                        your S. Tour and I suppose in your Zoology,</rs> is perhaps the worst in
                    either of those books.</p>
                <p>I must now conclude with returning to yourself and family all the compliments of
                    the season. I shall rejoice to hear the two agreeable young <q>"Prattlers"</q>
                    are in health.<note resp="editorial">Stuart is referring to Pennant's son and
                        daughter by his first wife, <persName ref="pe0219">Elizabeth (née
                            Falconer)</persName>, <persName ref="pe0236">David</persName>
                        and <persName ref="pe0234">Arabella</persName>, who Pennant alludes
                        to in the last lines of the <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0001">
                                <hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland
                                1769</hi>
                            </title>
                        </bibl>: <q>'finished my journey with a rapture of
                            which no fond parent can be ignorant, that of being again restored to
                            two innocent prattlers after an absence equally regretted by all
                            parties.'</q>
                        <bibl type="authorial">
                            <biblScope unit="page">p.220</biblScope>
                        </bibl>.</note> — I hope <persName ref="pe0101">Lewis</persName> has by this time recovered some
                    marrow to his bones, happy in being no longer in hazard of starving, far from
                    his beloved <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>, in the midst
                    of tempest-beaten barrenness; and that <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> possesses his soul in peace, perfectly secure from all the
                    dangers of the swelling deep.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am, D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Sir, with great esteem, your
                        most obliged and most humble Servant</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    </signed>.
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>at Downing</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Flintshire</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <handShift/>Birds</p>
                <p>M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Stuart</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>