<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0426">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Stuart to Thomas Pennant: description of Oransay and Colonsay</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP369</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <p>
                            <locus>5a-5c</locus>
                        </p>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    <date when="1773-12-04"/>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>

            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0647">Oransa</placeName>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0647">
                        <hi rend="underline">Oransa</hi>
                    </placeName> is
                    separated by a narrow sound from the island of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0649">
                        <hi rend="underline">Colonsay</hi>
                    </placeName> only at high water. It
                    is computed to be two miles long and one broad. It contains 610 Acres, 1 R. and
                    148. of arable ground, no meadow or green pasture, 256. Acres of meadow or green
                    pasture., 256. Acres of rocky green pasture, no moss, 122 Acres. of mountainous
                    ground. — It is all at present in the hands of <persName ref="pe0202">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>
                        Niel</persName>, Brother to <persName ref="pe00s52">the late M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi> Niel of <hi rend="underline">Colonsay</hi>
                    </persName>. He pays but 30£ Ster. of annual Rent for it. He
                    sows every year about 20 bolls of bear, &amp; plants 10 bolls of potatoes. —
                    uses <unclear reason="damage">dung</unclear> or shell-sand for manure —
                    maintains <gap reason="damage" unit="chars" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> milk-cows,
                    with their followers; eight or ten horses; a dozen of goats and 60 Irish sheep,
                    valued at <gap reason="damage" unit="chars" atLeast="3" atMost="5"/> shillings
                    each — exports to market every year from 60 to 80 head of black-cattle ––––– His
                    number of servants, as it the case in all the principal farms in the W. isles,
                    is very great. He has one principal labouring servant, who has 50 shillings
                        p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> year for his wages, and a stone of meal
                        p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> week for his maintenance; a principal hand
                    or overseer of his Cattle, whose wages are grass for two milk-cows and meal for
                    the maintenance of his family; a cow-herd; wages 12 Sh<hi rend="superscript">s.</hi> p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> half-year with shoes; another
                    cow-herd, wages <gap reason="damage" unit="chars" quantity="1"/> or 9 shillings
                        p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> half-year; a Calf-hand, wages five
                    shillings; a maid for keeping his house, wages <unclear reason="illegible">3</unclear> £ p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> year; principal dairy-maid,
                    wages 12 marks Scots p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> half-year; five other women
                    servants, wages of each five marks Scots p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                    half-year ––––– Besides these servants there are two other men, called by their
                    occupation <hi rend="underline">aoireannan</hi>, who have the charge of
                    labouring so much ground, and taking care of the cattle it <sic>mantains</sic>;
                    and have for their trouble grass for two milk-cows, and six sheep, the tenth
                    sheaf of the produce of the ground <unclear reason="damage">and</unclear> as
                    many potatoes as they choose to plant –––––</p>
                <p>The most numerous wild animals in this island are rabbits — There are likewise
                    rats and mice — The weesel is but seldom seen. –––––</p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0649">Colonsay</placeName>
                </p>
                <p>Though the islands of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0649">
                        <hi rend="underline">Colonsay</hi>
                    </placeName> and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0647">
                        <hi rend="underline">Oronsay</hi>
                    </placeName> do not probably derive their
                    names from any words in the Galic language, yet most of the farms and places in
                    them evidently do, as <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0891">
                        <hi rend="underline">Garv-alt</hi>
                    </placeName> i.e. the rough or rocky rivulet, <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0893">
                        <hi rend="underline">Macharabeg</hi>
                    </placeName> i.e.
                    the small field, <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0892">
                        <hi rend="underline">Ballyvory</hi>
                    </placeName> i.e. S<hi rend="superscript">t Mary's</hi>
                    town or hamlet, <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0895">
                        <hi rend="underline">Karra-more</hi>
                    </placeName> i.e. the great stone, <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0894">
                        <hi rend="underline">Kill-Oran</hi>
                    </placeName> i.e.
                    the church or burying place of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Ouran &amp;c.
                    —</p>
                <p>The island of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0649">
                        <hi rend="underline">Colonsay</hi>
                    </placeName> contains 1969 Acres, 2 R. &amp; 16 P. of arable
                    ground; 236 Acres 13 R., 24 P. of meadow and green pasture; 1693 Acres, 1 R. and
                    80 P. of rocky green pasture, 191 Acres and 1 R. of moss; and 3421 Acres and 2
                    R. of mountainous ground. –––––</p>
                <p>Oats, bear and potatoes are almost the only crops reared — The sowing of oats
                    begins about the middle of April. The common increase is that of three boles and
                    a half of oats for each boll that is sown; of bear, eight ––––– </p>
                <p>At an average 220 head of black-cattle are exported annually out of this island
                    –––––</p>
                <p>There are about 40 or 50 tun of Kelp exported every year, each tun of which is
                    sold at 3£ 10 sh. or 4£ Sterling. — It is cut down about the middle of April,
                    and exported about the beginning of August –––––</p>
                <p>There are 467 examinable persons in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0649">Colonsay</placeName>. The inhabitants here, as well as in most <unclear reason="damage">of the</unclear> other Western isles, very <unclear reason="damage">prolifick </unclear> having frequently twins <unclear reason="damage">at a birth.</unclear> They are subject to few diseases.
                        <sic>Ninty</sic> years is the greatest age to which they commonly arrive.
                    The <hi rend="underline">small-pox</hi> is said to visit them once in the six or
                    seven years. The <hi rend="underline">Civans</hi> likewise sometimes prevails
                    among them –––––<note type="editorial">Sibbens, also rendered 'sivvens',
                        'civvens', or here, 'civans', was a skin disease often associated with the
                        poor of Scotland in the eighteenth century. It was described by Pennant in
                        an appendix to his <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0010">
                                <hi rend="italic">Tour in Scotland 1772 Part II</hi>
                            (1776)</title>
                        </bibl>: <q>A Loathsome and very infectious disease of the
                            venereal kind, called the <hi rend="italic">Sivvens</hi>, has long
                            afflicted the inhabitants of the Highlands, and from thence some parts
                            of the Lowlands in <hi rend="italic">Scotland</hi>, even as far as the
                            border of <hi rend="italic">England</hi>. Tradition says that it was
                            introduced by the soldiers of <hi rend="italic">Cromwell</hi> garrisoned
                            in the Highlands.</q>
                        <bibl>
                            <biblScope unit="page">p.447</biblScope>
                        </bibl>.</note>
                </p>

                <p>The Cornish Chough and <sic>Stirlings</sic> are frequent in this island —
                    wood-cocks are said to visit it ––––– The Eider-Duck has been said to frequent
                    it's coast, and that of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0647">
                        <hi rend="underline">Oransa</hi>
                    </placeName>, for these thirty years past –––––</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin Dec<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                            4<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1773</placeName>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>In my last letter I proposed to send you some account of some round towers found
                    in the inland parts of the Highlands; where the Danes certainly never
                    penetrated. But as you express an anxiety for having the remainder of the notes
                    I happened to get down during your Voyage to the W. isles sent you soon, I shall
                    proceed to give you some more of them, and <unclear reason="damage">waive</unclear> the other subject at present –––––</p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0652">
                        <hi rend="underline">Staffa</hi>
                    </placeName>, I
                    am informed, has received many visits this last summer from motives of curiosity
                    — <persName ref="pe0053">MacQuary of Ulva</persName>, the Proprietor of
                    it, is much involved in his circumstances, but he now hopes that some virtuoso
                    will give him such a price for <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0652">the island of
                            <hi rend="underline">Staffa</hi>
                    </placeName>, as will enable him to
                    retrieve his fortune, though two years ago I dare say he would chearfully sell
                    it to any man for a few pounds Sterling –––––</p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="pe0073">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Samuel
                        Johnson</persName>, accompanied by <persName ref="pe0035">James
                        Boswel Esq.</persName>, has lately it seems, made a long excursion to the
                    North of Scotland and the W. isles. They had the misfortune of meeting at last
                    with very bad weather. They were storm-stayed in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0896">the island of <hi rend="underline">Coll</hi>
                    </placeName> for near a fortnight, and were all the time obliged
                    to feed upon oat-meal — <persName ref="pe0073">The D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                    </persName>, it is said, intends to publish <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0095">his
                    tour</title>
                    </bibl>; but even if he does, I suppose it will interfere very little with your
                    plan. </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I remain <lb/>Dear Sir <lb/>with great regard <lb/>your obliged and <lb/>humble
                        Servant</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>

            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <handShift/>
                    <persName ref="pe0023">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        Stuart</persName> on <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0647">oransay</placeName>
                    &amp; <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0649">Collonsay</placeName>
                </p>
                <dateline>Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    1773.</dateline>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>