<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0429">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Stuart to Thomas Pennant: supplementary to his descriptions of
                    islands</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP369</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>8/1-8/2</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    <date when="1774-01-07"/>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>

                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>

            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName> Jan<hi rend="superscript">y.</hi> 7<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> 1774</dateline>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Yours of Dec<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> 24<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> has
                    come safely to my hands –––––</p>
                <p>I have little doubt but the 500 £, which we were told that <persName ref="pe0363">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Campbell of Shawfield</persName> pays of feu
                    duty for <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0717">
                        <hi rend="underline">Ilay</hi>
                    </placeName>, is
                    Sterling and not Scotch money. It was the old rent paid for all that island.</p>
                <p>Almost all the W. islanders, as far as I could learn, still observe <hi rend="underline">Pasch</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Yule</hi> or Christmas,
                    as they did in <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0116">Martin</title>
                    </bibl>'s days.</p>
                <p>Eight days ago I sent you such remarks relative to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">
                        <hi rend="underline">Iona</hi>
                    </placeName> as I
                    thought would be of any service to you — As for the notes which I had taken down
                    when I visited that island formerly, which was as far as I remember in Aug<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> 1769, to prevent your being led into any mistake
                    I would only again beg of you to remember that all the lengths and distances
                    mentioned in them were only guessed at. Such as I told you of in my last letter
                    may I think be depended upon, as I was at the pains to measure them all,
                    excepting the length and breadth of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0976">
                        <hi rend="underline">Reilig-Ourain</hi>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial">x <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0976">
                            <hi rend="underline">Reilig-Ourain</hi>
                        </placeName> i.e. the burying-place of S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Ouran.</note> which I hope you have marked
                    down with accuracy in your own notes.</p>
                <p>I unluckily neglected to make any enquiry as to the name of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0985">the
                        little island, that forms the harbour on the E. side of the sound of <hi rend="underline">Iona</hi>
                    </placeName>, so that I cannot give you
                    information as to that particular —</p>
                <p>South of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0976">Ouran's Chapel</placeName> lies the grave stone of one
                    of the old Mull Doctors with the following inscription around it: <quote>Hic
                        jacet Isannes Betonus Maclenorum familæ medicus qui mortuus est 19 nowembris
                        anno Domini 1657, et ætatis suæ 63. Donaldus Betonus facit 1674.</quote>
                </p>
                <p>Near the head of the stone is cut the Coat-of-arms of the Betons, and below is
                    the following epitaph: <quote>
                        <lb/>Ecce cadit iaculo victrici mortis iniquæ <lb/>Qui toties alios solveral
                        ipse malis. <lb/>Soli Deo gloria. </quote>
                </p>
                <p> I have great doubts as to the justice of the interpretation given of the Galic
                    inscription upon the stone in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">
                        <hi rend="underline">I-colm-kill</hi>
                    </placeName> now not to be seen, but a
                    print of which is preserved in the <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0049">Phil.
                            Trans.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="vol">Vol. 22.</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="page">p.790</biblScope>
                    </bibl>: The meaning of the other
                    Galic inscription, which is still visible there, is tolerably clear –––––</p>
                <p>If I mistake not, you carried along with you specimens of the granite used in the
                    buildings in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">
                        <hi rend="underline">Iona</hi>
                    </placeName>. It
                    was taken, they told us, not from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0729">Mull</placeName>, but from
                    an island in the sound.</p>
                <p>I wrote you in my last the principal anecdotes I knew relative to the rural
                    œconomy of the inhabitants of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">
                        <hi rend="underline">I-colm-kill</hi>
                    </placeName> — They are all poor. They live much upon
                    fish, various kinds of which are caught in great quantities round the island.
                    Black or <hi rend="underline">graddan</hi> meal is mostly used. A <hi rend="underline">quern</hi> or hand-mill is kept in every family; but all
                    the possessions are <hi rend="underline">multured</hi> to a water miln
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0729">Mull</placeName>.</p>

                <p>Their houses are mean. They are all built near one another, and hard by the ruins
                    of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0975">the Nunnery</placeName>. They are thatched with bear straw,
                    which is always for this purpose pulled by the roots.</p>
                <p>As there does <add place="above">not</add> a single tree grow in the island, they
                    are at a loss for wood, even for the purposes of agriculture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">Peats</hi> and <hi rend="underline">turf</hi> are their only
                    fuel.</p>
                <p>In some of the higher grounds there is moss, but it has no depth, and it is mixed
                    with much earth and sand.</p>
                <p>I imagine there must certainly be a mistake, either in my information, or, in the
                    notes I gathered down, relative to the encrease of bear in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">
                        <hi rend="underline">Iona</hi>
                    </placeName>. It must
                    surely be greater at an average than four or five-fold. — Indeed I see great
                    reason to suspect that this is not the only instance in which there may have
                    been a danger of being led into a mistake. Notwithstanding the greatest care and
                    attention in making all proper inquiry, and the having recourse to the best
                    mediums of information which the different places visited could at the time
                    afford, yet in countries where few ever of the better and more intelligent
                    people are accustomed to make any nice observations of this kind, the falling in
                    some instances into error seems indeed unavoidable. Any inconsiderable mistakes
                    however which may thus creep <del rend="strikethrough">into</del> into
                            <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0008">your work</title>
                    </bibl>, can, upon
                    better information afterwards be easily amended in a second edition; and in the
                    mean time must be readily excused by all who are possessed of any degree of
                    candour —</p>
                <p>I shall endeavour to send you the remarks relative to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0653">
                        <hi rend="underline">Cana</hi>
                    </placeName> by to-morrow eight day's Post, or
                    sooner, if there is an opportunity — </p>
                <p>In the mean time, wishing you a good new-year, and many happy returns,</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I remain <lb/>Dear Sir <lb/>Your most obliged &amp; humble Serv<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                    </salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>

                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. with regard to any distances &amp;c. in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">
                            <hi rend="underline">Iona</hi>
                        </placeName> as have not been measured by
                        any certain medium, it is certainly better not to descend to any particulars
                        —</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <handShift/>
                    <persName ref="pe0023">M<hi rend="superscript">r J. Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>
                        Dec<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 31. &amp; Jan. 7 <hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1774.</p>
                <p>on <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">Iona</placeName> Tiends, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>