<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0430">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Stuart to Thomas Pennant, on the economy of Skye</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP369</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>9a-9l</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    <date when="1774-02-01"/>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>
                </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="underline">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Stuart. Feb. 1.
                    1774</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Skie</hi>
                    </placeName>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">owners 1.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">Tacksmen <unclear reason="illegible">1.</unclear>
                            </hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">Farm <unclear reason="illegible">Dikes</unclear>
                                3.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">Manure, Plough 5.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <unclear reason="illegible">Grain Harvest
                                    6.7.</unclear>
                            </hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <unclear reason="illegible">Drying Graddan
                                    8.11.</unclear>
                            </hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">Flax 13.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <unclear>Cattle 14.23.</unclear>
                            </hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> 25.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> 27.28</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> 29.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> 32.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> 34.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> 37.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> 39.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>—<hi rend="underline">
                                <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                                <unclear reason="illegible">40.</unclear>
                            </hi>
                        </item>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="lines" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/>
                    </list>
                    <note type="editorial">This appears to be a contents page to Stuart's manuscript on Skye, written in
                        Pennant's hand.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="enclosed">
                <p>
                    <handShift/>The present annual Rent of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">Sky</placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial" place="foot">x It's Galic name <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                            <hi rend="underline">Eilean
                            Sgitheanach</hi>
                        </placeName>
                    </note> 7000£ — belonging all to <persName ref="pe0446">MacLeod</persName> and <persName ref="pe0447">Sir Alexander Mac Donald</persName>, excepting a small property of
                        <persName ref="pe0358">Mac-Inn<unclear reason="illegible">on</unclear>
                    </persName>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">valued</unclear> at 200 £, and of <persName ref="pe0448">MacLeod of Raarsay</persName>'s rented at 100 £ <hi rend="underline">p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> ann</hi> ––––– </p>
                <p>The lands in this island partly possessed by small tenants, and partly in the
                    hands of Gentlemen. Tacksmen; <unclear/> have large extensive farms — In
                        <persName ref="pe0447">MacDonald</persName>'s country, which lies
                    all on the North coast and is divided into three great districts called
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0950">
                        <hi rend="underline">
                            <unclear reason="illegible">Trotternish</unclear>
                        </hi>
                    </placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0951">
                        <hi rend="underline">Strath</hi>
                    </placeName> and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0655">
                        <hi rend="underline">Slate</hi>
                    </placeName>, there will be about 40 such
                    Tacksmen, besides small tenants ––––– </p>
                <p>It is only in later times that any written tacks or leases have been given —
                    Formerly there was but a <unclear reason="illegible">verbal</unclear> promise
                    made before witnesses, attended with the ceremony of delivering at the same time
                    a little straw into the Tacksman's hands — There were hardly any instances
                    however of their being obliged to <unclear reason="illegible">asset</unclear> or
                    remove from the possessions. — Many of them considered themselves as the
                    descendents and friends of the great family on whom they depended, and held
                    their farms at an easy rent from father to son by a kind of <unclear>?</unclear>
                    or imaginary right called by the Highlanders <hi rend="underline">duchas</hi>,<hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial" place="foot">From <hi rend="underline">dùthaich</hi> a
                            <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" quantity="3"/> country</note> which
                    as long as any traces of the spirit of Chieftainship remained, was held sacred
                    and inviolable — Several of them likewise held their possessions by wadset, a
                    form of tenure by which the tenant lodges so much money in the <unclear reason="illegible">hands</unclear> of the Proprietor, the interest of which,
                    so long as the Capital remains unpaid, is considered as an equivalent in part or
                    whole, to the rent of his farm —</p>
                <p>The farms commonly <unclear reason="illegible">Rounded</unclear> with dikes made
                    of earth or soda, the repairing of which takes up a great part of their labour,
                    during summer <unclear reason="illegible">days</unclear> —</p>
                <p>But there are hardly any head-dikes to be seen, in order to separate their
                    hill-grass from the low-grounds, though they stand much in need of them — </p>
                <p>Sea tangle the most common manure for <hi rend="underline">bear</hi> — Little
                    kelp made upon the coast of this island — From what is manufactured of it
                    commonly 2 £ Sterl. of clear profit p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> tun —
                    Reckoned more beneficial however to use it as a manure.</p>
                <p>Small tenants, though their horses are idle, chuse rather to delve their ground
                    with the <hi rend="underline">crooked spade</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial" place="foot">This kind of spade, which is almost the only
                        one used in Sk<del rend="overstrike">
                            <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                        </del>ie called in Galic <hi rend="underline">cas-chrom</hi> i.e. the spade
                        with the crooked shank or handle ––––– </note> to till it with the plough —
                    Crop produced in this way observed to be better, — but the arable ground from
                    this circumstance wearing often an irregular and disagreeable aspect; as they
                    are not at pains to delve or sow at all the worst and most barren spots,
                    especially at the end of the different plots ––––– Computed that eight men will
                    delve as much ground in a day with the <hi rend="underline">crooked spade</hi>
                    as a plough is able to till ––––– </p>
                <p>Harrows commonly tyed to the horses tails — In wet ground, or where horses cannot
                    harrow properly <unclear reason="illegible">men and</unclear> women are employed
                    in breaking the ground with a block of wood having fine teeth and a long handle;
                    which they call a <hi rend="underline">raachgan</hi> ––––– </p>
                <p>Small black oats and potatoes the principal crops — The little <hi rend="underline">bear</hi> that is <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> sown very thin — The common return of <hi rend="underline">oats</hi> three or four-fold, of <hi rend="underline">bear</hi> from eight to sixteen ––––– </p>
                <p>The <hi rend="underline">bear</hi> when ripe always pulled by the root and the
                    straw preserved for thatching the houses, after cutting off the grain-end with a
                    hook</p>
                <p>— The corns shorn as high as possible as the only <add place="above">object</add>
                    is to <del rend="overstrike">collect the</del> collect the grain — The stubble
                    if there is not enough of <hi rend="underline">bear-straw</hi> for thatching
                    pulled likewise for his purpose by the root ––––– </p>
                <p>Corn as soon as it is cut down made unto small round heaps<hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial" place="foot">x These round heaps are called by the
                        natives <hi rend="underline">mulains</hi>—</note> of any indetermined number
                    of sheaves, <unclear reason="illegible">which are</unclear> thatched directly
                    with stubble pulled for that purpose, as they cannot depend a moment upon the
                    weather — Afterwards, if there is a fair hour these heaps are taken down now and
                    then in order to give them air, and new ones made up, which are thatched in the
                    same way.</p>
                <p>— By reason of the high and penetrating winds so common here, the corn soon dries
                    in this way and is then carried into the barnyards, where it is laid up in
                    stacks ––––– </p>
                <p>If they can, they shear their corns only when dry. If they are obliged however,
                    to <unclear reason="illegible">cut them</unclear> down wet, they <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> the single sheaves<hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial">Single sheaves sat up in this way, called <hi rend="underline">gabhair</hi> i.e. goats, from some resemblance they are
                        thought to bear to these animals ––––– </note> for some time standing on
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> till they are tolerably
                    dry, and then make round heaps of them.</p>
                <p>When they want to convert the corn into meal, if it is not so dry as to burn
                    readily, it is laid for a little upon a kiln with a slow fire — When taken off,
                    it is laid together in a heap <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> open fields, if it is a fair day <gap/> on the floor of the
                    kiln in bad weather. — Two women then take each of them constantly a handful
                    from this heap, <add place="above">and when the have</add> set fire to it, lay
                    it aside into a separate heap with <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> stick.<hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial" place="foot">x This stick they call <hi rend="underline">maig-araiguin</hi> from the nature of it's office ––––– </note> The
                    grain is then ––––– ––––– ––––– set into larger straw baskets, where two women
                    take hold of one another's arms, and <unclear reason="illegible">trample</unclear> upon it for some time with their naked feet till the
                    husks are in a great measure separated from it, singing merrily together Galic
                    Chorus songs all the while. Afterwards, when it is sufficiently winnowed, the
                    same two women carry it away to the house, and grind it together upon the <hi rend="underline">quern</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial" place="foot">x The <hi rend="underline">quern</hi> is in
                        Galic called <hi rend="underline">bra'</hi>—</note> or hand miln, singing
                    then likewise Galic songs </p>
                <p> —The meal; which is of a dark grey colour, is baked into thick round cakes,
                    which are set starting by <unclear reason="illegible">the</unclear> side of a
                    stone near live coals in order to harden — As by thus burning the corn the seed
                    itself is in reality not nearly so much deprived of it's natural juices as in
                    the common method of kiln-drying elsewhere, the bread it is said, is found by
                    experience to be much lighter and more easily digested than the white oat-bread
                    used in other parts. It does not keep fresh for any time. It is baked therefore
                    every day and sometimes twice a day. It is called <hi rend="underline">graddan</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                    <note type="authorial">x From <hi rend="underline">grad</hi> quick or expeditious.</note> bread from the
                    quickness and expedition with which it is prepared. There have been many
                    instances of <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> hungry stranger
                    coming into a house without the least meal in it at the time or any grain in the
                    barn, and yet in a few hours <unclear reason="illegible">he has</unclear> had a
                    plentiful repast <unclear reason="illegible">from</unclear> the corn which when
                    he came was seen growing in the fields.</p>
                <p>As the practice of burning the Corn in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName> and some of the other W. isles is
                    so destructive to the <unclear reason="illegible">provender</unclear> which
                    might otherwise be p<gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="4" atMost="6"/>ed for the sake of the cattle, it is now much discouraged by all the
                    Proprietors, and in the course of a few years. It is a practice however, without
                    doubt, of very remote antiquity:— One would be almost tempted to think that the
                    ancient Romans, or at least their famed progenitors, had precisely the same rule
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="3" atMost="4"/>: </p>
                <p>(See Virgil's description in the first <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" quantity="3"/> of the process used for converting the corn of <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="4" atMost="5"/> into meal. <gap reason="illegible" unit="lines" quantity="1"/>&amp;c.)<note type="editorial">Possibly a reference to <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0532">'Moretum'</title>
                        </bibl>, a Latin poem attributed to Virgil which
                        depicts the use of a quern.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Hardly any lintseed sown especially by the poorer tenants, excepting a dwarf
                    degenerate species, which does not grow above <unclear reason="illegible">six</unclear> inches high and the seed of which had been preserved by the
                    islanders time out of mind. When pulled it is <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> steept in water as in other parts. It is tyed
                    together in <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                    parcels, which are <unclear reason="illegible">hung up in</unclear> the house
                    near the fire. When these parcels are sufficiently dry they are well beaten with
                    a wooden <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/>; and instead of
                    being <unclear reason="illegible">switched</unclear> are then forced frequently
                    through a wooden instrument shaped somewhat like a Barber's toupee-tongs which
                    they <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="4" atMost="6"/>-tongs —</p>
                <p>The best and richest soil in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName> is at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0953">
                        <hi rend="underline">Mugestot</hi>
                    </placeName>.
                    Without any manure it is <gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="words"/> to
                    yield crops so rank that <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> greatest <add place="above">danger</add> lies in their being
                    lost <gap reason="illegible" quantity="1" unit="words"/> harvest by lodging
                    —</p>
                <p>Little meadow-ground in this island — Hardly any hay preserved, except at
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0661">
                        <hi rend="underline">Talisker</hi>
                    </placeName> and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0953">
                        <hi rend="underline">Mugestot</hi>
                    </placeName> ––––– </p>
                <p>The principal dependence of the people of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">Sky</placeName> is upon their black cattle, and they are allowed to <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/> in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0711">the Highlands</placeName>. This indeed is the staple
                        <unclear reason="illegible">commodity</unclear> for in such nature seems
                        <unclear reason="illegible">principally to have intended</unclear> their
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="3" atMost="4"/> many parts <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                    <unclear reason="damage">Esteemed</unclear> to be good, and from abundance of
                    natural manures and other circumstances there are all the advantages that could
                    be wished for in order to improve <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> highest pitch of perfection, yet the climate is
                    such, particularly <unclear reason="illegible">at the</unclear> harvest, as must
                    ever render the returns of the farmer uncertain —</p>
                <p>The rearing of good black Cattle is the principal object, which all the
                    inhabitants of Sky propose to themselves, <unclear reason="illegible">when
                        in</unclear> company together <unclear reason="illegible"> it is</unclear>
                    often the great topick of <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/>. They are very studious to furnish themselves, with a good kind
                    of <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> and to improve the breed
                    by getting the best and most <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/>
                    bulls. — Particular <unclear reason="illegible">care taken</unclear> in rearing
                    the calves and <unclear reason="illegible">more</unclear> or less hardy, and
                    proportioning the <unclear reason="illegible">sizes</unclear> of the cattle to
                    the nature of the farm — After the first five or six days <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> commonly allowed to
                        <unclear reason="illegible">suck only</unclear> twice a day; but such as are
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="3" atMost="4"/> observed to
                    thrive much <unclear reason="illegible">better</unclear> by being allowed
                    constantly to follow <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> mother
                    than though they had the <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/>
                    quantity of milk given <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="3" atMost="4"/> periods — <unclear reason="illegible">Allowed to suck
                        more</unclear> plentifully <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="2"/> than in the morning <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> too
                    great <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="2"/> than is apt to make
                        <unclear reason="illegible">them</unclear> sleepy and indolent all the day
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> sucking some water given
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> them to drink
                    as the milk itself is thought to create a drought — </p>
                <p>During the heat of summer particular <unclear>pains taken</unclear> to keep <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> constant motion in
                    order to <gap reason="illegible" unit="lines" quantity="2"/> their indulging
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> indolent or lazy
                    dispositions — Only one calf <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/>
                    by <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> of such cows as
                    are <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/>nded for
                    yielding milk — Allowed in this case to suck but one of <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> in the morning, and the other in the evening, as
                    sucking is much severer upon the <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> than milking — Rearing <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> the great object — In <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName> therefore
                    and all the other Cattle <unclear reason="illegible">country in the</unclear>
                    Highlands, seldom are butter or cheese made but what <unclear reason="illegible">is barely</unclear> sufficient for serving the several <unclear reason="illegible">families</unclear> — The cattle of this island <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> as they are in the habit of
                    yielding <unclear reason="illegible">a</unclear> great quantity of milk during
                        <unclear reason="illegible">summer and none at all in winter</unclear>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">observed to better for</unclear>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> and serving the purposes of
                    the butcher, than for making any other returns –––––</p>
                <p>Particular care taken <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> during
                    winter, — brought <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/>
                    to the best pasture along <unclear reason="illegible">with</unclear> the
                    milk-cows, or to a certain warm spot by themselves — Attention likewise paid to
                    cows <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/>
                </p>
                <p>Only one spot of ground inclosed with a high dike in <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> out as a fold for <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> black Cattle during all summer
                    — Kept in the <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="3" atMost="5"/>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">higher</unclear> grounds, in order to <unclear reason="illegible">pasture</unclear> as much as possible <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> part of the low
                    ground for winter pasture — This the only provision <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> for their cattle against the <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> of this season —
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="5" atMost="7"/>ures commonly
                    housed then and no provender preserved for them —</p>
                <p>The <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> when accessible, proves
                        <unclear>the greatest</unclear> relief to black Cattle during <unclear reason="illegible">severe</unclear> storms in winter and spring.</p>
                <p>As <del rend="overtyped">
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    </del> the food they find there is of a laxative nature it prevents that
                    costiveness which from the <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/>
                    quantity of their <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> at that
                    time <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> be so liable
                    to, and <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> their
                    appetite for digesting any other coarse food they are able to gather — Though at
                    a distance and <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> of
                    the sea, it is pretty <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> by a kind of <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/> the
                    poor creatures of <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/>
                    repair all regularly <unclear reason="illegible">every day</unclear> to the
                    shore at <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="2"/> –––––</p>
                <p>Fish-oil an established remedy for costiveness, <unclear reason="illegible">which</unclear> the cattle happen to be <unclear reason="illegible">supplied</unclear> with — This disorder, when excessive, apt to <unclear reason="illegible">end in a</unclear> dissantery called by the natives <hi rend="underline">dù<gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" quantity="1"/>g</hi>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="3" atMost="4"/>r i.e.
                    the black disease, perhaps from the greenish colour, which the fæces <unclear reason="illegible">are then</unclear> observed to have ––––– </p>
                <p>The greatest and most glaring <unclear reason="illegible">deficiency</unclear> in
                    the management of the <unclear reason="illegible">Rearing of black</unclear>
                    Cattle in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName> lies in <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> of no kind of provision against the <unclear reason="illegible">precarities</unclear> of spring and winter
                    notwithstanding that from this very circumstance they often lose <unclear reason="illegible">a third</unclear> of their whole stock —</p>
                <p> Though they had plenty of provender it would perhaps be improper to house their
                    cattle or make them any other than a hardy breed, fit for travelling at a
                    distance to markets, and for fattening readily when brought to richer pastures
                    in the South — But surely, were they to give <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> burning their corns, and properly
                    encouraged by the Proprietors to <unclear reason="illegible">enclose
                        their</unclear> several farms with good stone fences so as <unclear reason="illegible">to enable</unclear> them to raise turnips and <unclear reason="illegible">sow</unclear> grasses, they might <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> safety a greater number of cattle than
                    they do at present, <unclear reason="illegible">raise those</unclear> of a <add place="above">better</add> breed; and prevent any danger of <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> either actually
                    starved or brought very low in a bad winter or spring — If <unclear reason="illegible">either natural</unclear> or sowed grasses were preserved
                    early so as to be fit for cutting down about the middle or end of <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>, the Crop would be seldom
                        <unclear reason="illegible">lost</unclear> through the inclemency of the
                    weather ––––– </p>
                <p>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">Another</unclear> capital defect in the management
                    of the Rearers of black Cattle in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">Sky</placeName>, is the over-stocking their several farms — Summer <unclear reason="illegible">grass</unclear> in this island for a much greater number
                    of cattle than can be kept alive in winter and spring — Even in summer however
                    sometimes overstock as the cattle from all the <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> islands of <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0954">
                            <hi rend="underline">Harris</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0955">
                            <hi rend="underline">Uist</hi>
                        </placeName>
                    </unclear> &amp;c. are commonly brought up by the
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">Sky</placeName>
                    <hi rend="underline">Drovers</hi>, and remain after as a super-cargo on their
                    grounds ––––– </p>
                <p>The horses small, but durable and hardy — The common <unclear reason="illegible">price</unclear> of each, 3 or 4 £ <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="1" atMost="4"/> Very few exported — Never fed or housed even in
                    time of labour — At evening, when the work of the day is over, <unclear reason="illegible">the two</unclear> fore-feet of <unclear reason="illegible">each pair of them</unclear> commonly tyed together with a
                    rope made of heather to prevent their getting <unclear reason="illegible">off at
                        a distance</unclear> from Masters who reward their services with so much
                    cruelty —</p>
                <p>Not much employed in labour at any other time, and well fed in summer ––––– </p>
                <p>The number of goats and <add place="above">small</add> sheep reared on each farm
                    only sufficient for serving the purposes of the family — All of them in this
                    island at the entire disposal of the women— </p>
                <p> A number of servants employed by each <unclear reason="illegible">Tacksman in
                            <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">Sky</placeName>
                    </unclear>, — commonly a
                    principal servant or Overseer, 3 or 4 other menservants, two herds, two dairy
                    maids, 2 or 3 maid-servants, and 2 or 3 old women for burning and grinding
                        <unclear reason="illegible">the corn</unclear> and baking the bread — The
                    common wages of men-servants 30 or 40 sh. p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> ann
                    with shoes; of maid-servants 6 or 8 marks with shoes and liberty to spin some
                    clothes to the <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> — Indulged
                    besides however sometimes in weaning a calf or two or three sheep along with the
                    common stock— </p>
                <p>The food of servants and the lower class of people very poor — Only two meals
                    each day, one at eleven in the forenoon and the other at 7 or 8 in the
                    afternoon—</p>
                <p>One dairy-maid, and one herd reckoned necessary for taking care of <unclear reason="illegible">every two dozen</unclear>
                    <del rend="overstrike">of every two dozen</del> of milk-cows — They have a
                    privilege of drinking always some of the milk at the fold; and the stranger
                    never passes by without having some of it offered to him —</p>
                <p>When a Tacksman has a greater <unclear reason="illegible">farm</unclear> than he
                    can well manage himself, he often sets part of it to a <hi rend="underline">bowman</hi>,<hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial">
                        <hi rend="superscript">x</hi> Called in the Gal. lang.
                            <hi rend="underline">Aireach</hi>.</note> who takes care of his stock of
                    cattle upon it, and obliges himself to give him about 4 stone of cheese <unclear reason="illegible">&amp;</unclear> 2 stone of butter for each <unclear reason="illegible">couple</unclear> of milk-cows during every year he is
                    pleased to employ him — If there is any arable ground, <unclear reason="illegible">he</unclear> is provided in horses and a plough for
                    tilling it, and seed for sowing it; and his labour is rewarded by a <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> of the produce and by grass
                    for two or three milk-cows along with the rest ––––– </p>
                <p>Publick roads much needed in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">Sky</placeName> —
                    For want of them no carts or <hi rend="underline">sledges</hi> hitherto used
                    there —</p>
                <p>The houses of the common tenants all <unclear reason="illegible">with a</unclear>
                    roof, thatched with straw which is kept firmly on by cross ropes to the lower
                    extremity <sic>of which</sic> are suspended a number of stones in order to make
                    constant pressure — The foundation, for the sake of shelter, often sunk much
                    under ground — The walls commonly of stone very thick lined in the middle with
                    earth in order to prevent the cold Northern blasts from penetrating through
                    them—</p>
                <p>An earthen porch built often at the door –––––</p>
                <p>The people in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> the late ferment occasioned
                    by augmenting their rents to all appearance extremely happy — fond of society
                    and living in peace and friendship together — of an open and chearful
                    countenance — beyond conception kind and hospitable to strangers — fond of
                    musick and dancing — till of late much attached to their Chief, whom they
                    considered as the Guardian and Head of their several families —</p>
                <p>There is no labour they go about but they join frequently in singing Galic Songs,
                    the musick of which is well adapted to the particular species of work; and this
                    practice is observed to have such a visible influence in raising and supporting
                    their spirits and thereby <sic>expeding</sic> their labour, that care is
                    commonly taken that the song shall not fail— At <unclear reason="illegible">shearing</unclear> in particular it is pleasant in a good day to hear at a
                    distance perhaps 30 or 40 voices joining altogether in concert. When the song
                    and work <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> on to the
                    Overseer's mind, he <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" quantity="1"/> and then
                    expresses his <unclear reason="illegible">approbation</unclear> by a loud
                    inarticulate roar. When there is another company shearing within reach of his
                    voice their Overseer seldom fails to give another roar in return, to raise an
                    emulation and let him know that he thinks his own company behave equally well
                    —</p>
                <p>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">Almost</unclear> all particularly the women, have a
                    good musical ear and good voices, much improved no doubt by being in the habit
                    of singing from infancy — They have likewise a good lively imagination, many of
                    the best modern Galic songs having been composed <unclear reason="illegible">in</unclear> this island ––––– </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">Sky</placeName> famous for Pipers ––––– None in
                    any part of the Highlands thought to be sufficiently qualified till they pass
                        <unclear reason="illegible">an affirmation</unclear> with the <unclear reason="illegible">
                        <hi rend="underline">Mac Cruimer</hi>
                    </unclear> or <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">Piper</unclear>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> the families of
                        <unclear reason="illegible">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod</unclear> and
                        M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Donald those formerly held the office
                    hereditary. The art and the emoluments descended from father to son. — There is
                    at present a great number of <hi rend="underline">p<gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" quantity="6"/>hts</hi> or bag-pipe airs, the most of which
                    have been composed by their Ancestors, who are said to have greatly excelled
                    them in that art — They own however, that if tradition can be depended upon, the
                        bag-pipe<hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial" place="foot">In Galic Piob.—</note> is <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> instrument of the
                    old <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> the
                    Highlanders, and that they borrowed it <unclear reason="illegible">originally</unclear> from the Danes. Formerly the harp was probably the
                    only musical instrument known in these parts. Till about <add place="above">sixty years ago</add>
                    <hi rend="underline">Mac-Leod</hi> and Mac-Donald kept Harpers in their
                    families, as well as Pipers. A room is still pointed out in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0667">the old ruinous castle of <hi rend="underline">Dun-tuilm</hi>
                    </placeName> which is called <hi rend="underline">seomar-nan-clèrsaireag</hi>
                    i.e the room of the Harpers ––––– </p>
                <p>This island long ago famous for second sighted people — and there are some in it
                    who still <unclear reason="illegible">pretend</unclear> to this wonderful
                    facility. But they are always persons of the weakest intellect, and of a
                    vapourish imagination. Their imposition without doubt is not always designed.
                    They are sometimes first deluded themselves into a belief of the reality of
                    their pretended visions; and they too easily delude their superstitious
                    brethren. But with the more sensible part their vain predictions are <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="1" atMost="5"/> justly contemned— </p>
                <p>No wood in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName>, except a little at <unclear reason="damage">Kyl-arrain</unclear> and in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0655">Slate</placeName> — Timber imported every year from the main land with
                    considerable trouble and expence — In places that are tolerably sheltered
                    plantations would certainly thrive. But any tryals that have already been made
                    in places much exposed to the Northern blast have not answered expectations
                    ––––– </p>
                <p>A narrow seam of Coals seen in the middle of immense <hi rend="underline">whin</hi> rocks at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0956">
                        <hi rend="underline">Portree</hi>
                    </placeName>,<hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                   <note type="authorial" place="foot">
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0956">
                            <hi rend="underline">Port-righ</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <unclear reason="illegible">i.e.</unclear> The Kings harbour —</note> and in
                    one or two other places in this island — but not worth the labour <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> of working ––––– </p>
                <p>More petrifactions found upon the coast than in any other of the W. isles, as <hi rend="underline">Belemnites Cornu Ammonis</hi>; immense rocks of limestone
                    full of petrifyed shells &amp;c. —</p>
                <p>White marble in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0951">
                        <hi rend="underline">Strath</hi>
                    </placeName>, black in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0957">
                        <hi rend="underline">Torrin</hi>
                    </placeName> ––––– </p>
                <p>Beautiful rock-marl in great abundance in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0951">
                        <hi rend="underline">Strath</hi>
                    </placeName> — evidently formed from
                    lime-stone — The rock appearing firm and solid in <unclear reason="illegible">some</unclear> parts above, in the <unclear reason="illegbile">mixture</unclear> retaining it's light blue colour and a little of it's
                    hardness but really formed into a marl, and below the marl quite soft and a fine
                    white colour ––––– </p>
                <p>Elf-shot arrows frequently found here ––––– </p>
                <p>Many druidical Circles to be seen in different parts of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName> — the stones
                    of which they consist low and small — Circles commonly but 13 or 14 feet in
                        diam<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> — Called by the natives <hi rend="underline">tighe-nan-driuneach</hi> i.e. the houses of the Druids.</p>
                <p>Some very large <hi rend="underline">Cairns</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                    <note type="authorial">heaps</note> are to be seen in different
                    parts. In the middle of such as have been taken down for the sake of the stone
                    in building <hi rend="underline">dikes</hi>, small earthen cairns with some
                    ashes in them have been found ––––– </p>
                <p>In <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0952">
                        <hi rend="underline">Raarsay</hi>
                    </placeName>
                    and in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName> there are some flat stones of about <add place="above">4 or</add> five feet in diameter, which were probably once the altars of
                    one of the druidical divinities — The superstitious, attached to the customs of
                    their ancestors, still pour at certain times a libation of milk upon them. They
                    are called <hi rend="underline">clachan-a'-Ghruagaich</hi> i.e. the stones of
                    the Gruagach. A particular account of the common belief of the islanders with
                    regard to this superior Being is given by <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0116">
                            <hi rend="underline">Martin</hi>
                        </title>
                    </bibl>. ––––– </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
                <dateline>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName> Feb<hi rend="superscript">y.</hi> 1. 1774 —</dateline>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I was favoured with yours of Jan<hi rend="superscript">y.</hi> 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> yesterday morning, inclosing <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0008">a specimen of your Tour</title>
                    </bibl> with which
                    I am much pleased — It gave me no small pain however to find that the remarks
                    relative to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0651">Iona</placeName> were <unclear reason="illegible">too late —</unclear> All I can say is that though a
                    Highlander <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="2" atMost="3"/> not
                    surely lay the smallest claim to the "Second sight," otherwise my desire of
                        <unclear reason="illegible">being of</unclear>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/>le service to you
                    in my power <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="2" atMost="4"/>
                    prevented any of my letters from being <unclear reason="illegible">as</unclear>
                    far distanced, though part of my most necessary business in other respects
                    should be allowed to stand — I now suspect however that my first letter must
                    have <unclear reason="illegible">loitered</unclear> some days betwixt this and
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0295">Crieff</placeName>, as I was obliged to
                    send it by an uncertain hand — I send you inclosed part of the remarks on
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">
                        <hi rend="underline">Sky</hi>
                    </placeName>,
                    which I would fain hope may come to your h<gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="3" atMost="4"/> in due time — The remaining part is sent you <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="3"/> Cover by the same
                    Post — After leaving this island excepting some names of places, there will I
                    think be but few new observations of any consequence that I can communicate unto
                    you — <persName ref="pe0312">Achalader</persName> and <persName ref="pe0449">my father</persName> are in health and much at your
                    service.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I remain <lb/>Dear Sir <lb/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> great sincerity <lb/>Your most humble Serv<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> </salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Downing</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Flintshire</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>S. Britain—</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>