<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0432">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Stuart to Thomas Pennant: remarks on Breadalbane and Rannoch</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP369</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>11/1a-11/3c</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    <date when="1774-04-07"/>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>

                <language ident="en">English</language>

                <language ident="gd">Gaelic</language>

            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Killin</placeName> Ap<hi rend="superscript">l.</hi>
                </dateline>
                <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                <p>I was favoured with your obliging Letter of 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    March just as I was leaving home this day fortnight in order to attend another
                    meeting of the Presbytery of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0226">Dumbarton</placeName> and have not till now had any opportunity of writing
                    you in return to it ––––– </p>
                <p>It gives me no small uneasiness to find that none of the letters I wrote you
                    relative to your voyage after leaving <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0718">
                        <unclear reason="illegible">the island of Rum</unclear>
                    </placeName>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="words" atLeast="1" atMost="2"/> have come to your
                    hands in due time, especially as I thought they contained <unclear reason="illegible">many</unclear> of the most material remarks which I had
                    to communicate. In the course of corresponding with you upon that subject, I
                    certainly met with many necessary avocations which I could not have foreseen;
                    and you are accordingly so good as to forgive me, but I can hardly altogether
                    forgive myself. My principal error was in not informing myself better as to the
                    precise time of your publication. I cannot account however for the unexpected
                    delay you mention with regard to the letters you received relative to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0715">Sky</placeName> &amp;c, as from the moment I came to
                    understand that your Printers went on with such rapidity I did not omit a single
                    opportunity of writing you till all the observations which I had to send you
                    upon the voyage were exhausted. Were I not from one of your letters led to
                    imagine that you proposed to conclude the whole of your last <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0008">Scotch Tour, and not only the
                            first volume</title>
                    </bibl> of it, at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0266">
                        <hi rend="underline">Ardmaddy</hi>
                    </placeName>, I would have likewise
                        <sic>proceeded</sic> to send you Remarks relative to this country, at
                    greater length than my time will now permit me ––––– </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0213">
                        <hi rend="underline">Glenurchay</hi>
                    </placeName>
                </p>
                <p>The river which runs in this valley and from which it derives it's name is called
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0988">
                        <hi rend="underline">Urchay</hi>
                    </placeName> — Plenty of trout and some salmon are caught upon
                    it. —</p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0989">
                        <hi rend="underline">Clachan-dysart</hi>
                    </placeName> is the name of the parish in this country,
                    of which <persName ref="pe0158">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Intyre</persName> is Minister. —</p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0214">
                        <hi rend="underline">Dalmaly</hi>
                    </placeName> is
                    the name of the inn where you lodged. In order to accomodate the Publick
                        <persName ref="pe0036">Lord Breadalbane</persName> has been at the
                    expence of building a good convenient house here, at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0212">
                        <hi rend="underline">Tyndrom</hi>
                    </placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">
                        <hi rend="underline">Killin</hi>
                    </placeName> and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0103">
                        <hi rend="underline">Kenmore</hi>
                    </placeName> to each of which he has
                    annexed a farm at <sic>any</sic> easy Rent —</p>
                <p>The same customs and manners prevail nearly here as upon the W. coast ––––– </p>
                <p> Upon leaving <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0213">
                        <hi rend="underline">Glenurchay</hi>
                    </placeName>, which is the last of what are properly
                    called Cattle-countries that you had occasion to pass through, you have a good
                    opportunity afforded you of adding any general observations or reflections upon
                    the management of black Cattle or the rural œconomy of the N. Highlanders. Any
                    hints of that nature that occurred to me I have already communicated to you in
                    one or other of the last letters I wrote you ––––– </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">Breadalbane</placeName>
                </p>
                <p>You entered into the district of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">
                        <hi rend="underline">Breadalbane</hi>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">*</hi>
                    <note type="authorial" place="foot">* <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">
                            <hi rend="underline">Braid-albin</hi>
                        </placeName> i.e. the higher part
                        of Scotland.</note> a little West from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0212">
                        <hi rend="underline">Tyndrom</hi>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">†</hi>
                    <note type="authorial" place="foot">† <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0212">
                            <hi rend="underline">Tigh-an-drom</hi>
                        </placeName> i.e. the house of the
                        height.</note> where the waters divide and run both into the W. and E. sea —
                    The lead mines near <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0212">
                        <hi rend="underline">Tyndrom</hi>
                    </placeName> succeed at present pretty well. The richest
                    part of the vein has always been found to be near the top of the hill. The ore
                    is now smelted in the country and some silver has been extracted from it —</p>
                <p>The valley which you entered into after leaving <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0212">
                        <hi rend="underline">Tyndrom</hi>
                    </placeName> is called <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0274">
                        <hi rend="underline">Strath-fillan</hi>
                    </placeName>,
                    from <hi rend="underline">S<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Fillan</hi> who spent
                    the latter part of his days here, and whose memory the inhabitants still greatly
                    revere. You saw the <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0990">
                        <hi rend="underline">holy
                            pool</hi>
                    </placeName> in the river which is thought to derive all it's
                    virtue from his benediction, and to which, upon particular days numbers of
                    persons repair from distant countries every summer, and particularly lunaticks
                    and mad-people, in hopes of being cured of their diseases by being plunged
                    thrice in the pool, and afterwards lyed down all night in the Chapel or
                    preaching-house on the cold floor. The cure <sic>administred</sic> in this way
                    has in some instances been such as to put a speedy period to the sorrows of this
                    life. ––––– </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0274">Strath-fillan</placeName> is part of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">the parish of Killin</placeName>, which is one of the
                    most extensive and populous in this part of the Highlands. Since you passed
                    through this country <persName ref="pe0462">Lady Glenurchay</persName>
                    with that laudable zeal for advancing the interests of religion so uncommon
                    among persons of her fortune and rank in this age of luxury and refinement, has
                    determined to mortify a considerable sum for supporting a Minister or Preacher
                    who is after this constantly to reside here, <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" quantity="1"/> has already built a good house for him, to which
                        <persName ref="pe0036">Lord Breadalbane</persName> has been so good
                    as to add a glebe ––––– </p>
                <p>This part of the country is now almost entirely under south-country sheep which
                    have hitherto answered very well, and turn out to much greater advantage than
                    black Cattle.</p>
                <p>The only Proprietors here are <persName ref="pe0036">Lord
                        Breadalbane</persName>, <persName ref="pe0464">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Campbell of Lochdochart</persName> whose
                    House you would have seen upon the North side of the river and <persName ref="pe0465">the King</persName>, who has here but one farm being a
                    part of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0991">the forfeited estate of
                        Perth</placeName>. — Inclosures, planting and other improvements being to be
                    carried on with greater spirit even in this higher part of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">Breadalbane</placeName> than in most places upon the
                    W. coast ––––– </p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0817">
                        <hi rend="underline">Lochdochart</hi>
                    </placeName> is the name of the lake which you passed by at
                    the foot of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0815">
                        <hi rend="underline">Ben-more</hi>
                    </placeName>,<hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                    <note type="authorial" place="foot">x <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0815">
                            <hi rend="underline">Beinn-mhòr</hi>
                        </placeName> i.e. the great mountain
                        —</note> the loftiest mountain in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">
                        <hi rend="underline">Breadalbane</hi>
                    </placeName> —</p>
                <p>
                    <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> english miles East from
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0212">
                        <hi rend="underline">Tyndrom</hi>
                    </placeName>, near the publick road, and opposite to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0992">
                        <hi rend="underline">Achessan</hi>
                    </placeName> a farm
                    belonging to <persName ref="pe0466">MacNab</persName> of that ilk, and
                    now likewise under South-country sheep, you saw a small lake remarkable for
                    having the only really floating island in it I ever saw.<note type="editorial">The measurements given by Stuart indicate a body of water considerably
                        smaller than the nearby <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0817">Loch
                            Dochart</placeName> or <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0993">Loch
                            Iubhair</placeName>, perhaps <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0994">Lochan Dùn
                            Saoraich</placeName> slightly further east.</note> I have seen it in the
                    space of a few days driven by the winds to quite different end of the lake, so
                    that there can be no doubt of it's actually floating — The lake itself is about
                    200 feet long and 60 feet broad. <sic>The is</sic> 51 feet long, and 2y broad.
                    At the edge it is about 25 inches in thickness. <sic>The it</sic> consists of is
                    mostly mossy. It is covered with coarse grasses and willows. A young birch-tree,
                    about three feet and a half high, likewise grows upon it ––––– </p>
                <p>The valley you now entered into is called <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0276">
                        <hi rend="underline">Glendochart</hi>
                    </placeName>, and the river which runs
                    in it that of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0995">
                        <hi rend="underline">Dochart</hi>
                    </placeName>. This river a few years ago answered better for
                    pearl-fishing than perhaps any other in the Highlands. Some of the largest and
                    best were found in it, and sold mostly to merchants in Perth. It is computed
                    that in the space of two or three years this commodity brought at least 300 £
                    Sterl. of money to the country —</p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0276">
                        <hi rend="underline">Glendochart</hi>
                    </placeName> is in general to bare of wood both for
                    ornament and shelter. This defect you would observe, <persName ref="pe0467">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Campbell of <hi rend="underline">Achlyne</hi>
                    </persName> has endeavoured to remedy in
                    the neighbourhood of his own house by considerable young plantations of fir on
                    each side of the river. With an uncommon degree of publick spirit he had shewen
                    a good example to others by extensive inclosures (the first capital step in the
                    improvement of any country) both upon his estate in the country, and at
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0299">the W. end of <hi rend="underline">Lochern</hi>
                    </placeName>, where he has likewise at no small expence
                    built <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0997">a commodious Inn</placeName>, for the
                    refreshment of Strangers just before they ascend <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0996">the hill of <hi rend="underline">Larig-<unclear reason="illegible">iele</unclear>
                        </hi>
                    </placeName>, in their way to
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">Breadalbane</placeName> ––––– </p>
                <p>You'll remember that <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0995">the river <hi rend="underline">Dochart</hi>
                    </placeName> where you crossed it along two
                    bridges just as you entered into <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">
                        <hi rend="underline">Killin</hi>
                    </placeName>
                    <hi rend="superscript">x</hi>
                    <note type="authorial" place="foot">x Commonly thougt to be <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">
                            <hi rend="underline">Cill-Fhinn</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        i.e. the burying-place of Fingal. His supposed grave is still pointed
                        out.</note> divides into two branches, and forms two small islands planted
                    with first, the eastmost of which is called <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0998">
                        <hi rend="underline">Inish-buy</hi>
                    </placeName>,<hi rend="superscript">†</hi>
                    <note type="authorial" place="foot">† <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0998">
                            <hi rend="underline">Inis-bui</hi>
                        </placeName>, i.e. the green island
                        –––––</note> and is exceedingly romantick and picturesque, especially when
                    the river is high, and forms one continued broken Cascade on each side —</p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1000">
                        <hi rend="underline">Finlarig</hi>
                    </placeName>,
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1001">
                        <hi rend="underline">Achmore</hi>
                    </placeName>, and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1001">
                        <hi rend="underline">Kinell</hi>
                    </placeName> it will be needless to describe
                    to you. — Near the last of these there is the most entire Druidical Circle which
                    remains in this part of the Highlands. It consists of six large stones fixed at
                    equal distances from each other — You may remember to have seen another
                    Druidical circle at <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1002">
                        <hi rend="underline">Lawers</hi>
                    </placeName> on the N. Side of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0104">Loch-tay</placeName>, but it is not nearly so entire
                    as this ––––– </p>
                <p>If you thing it proper to give any account of the <hi rend="underline">round
                        towers</hi> found in this country and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0105">Glenlyon</placeName>, you have a better opportunity of bringing it in when
                    passing through this Country than you could have had anywhere else. I wrote you
                    fully already with regard to these in my Letter relative to <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0721">
                        <hi rend="underline">Glenelg</hi>
                    </placeName>––––– </p>
                <p>The other river which passes by <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">
                        <hi rend="underline">Killin</hi>
                    </placeName> and <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0999">
                        <hi rend="underline">Finlarig</hi>
                    </placeName>, and
                    joins the <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0995">
                        <hi rend="underline">Dochart</hi>
                    </placeName> before they both discharge themselves into
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0104">
                        <hi rend="underline">Loch-tay</hi>
                    </placeName>, is called <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1003">
                        <hi rend="underline">Lochy</hi>
                    </placeName> ––––– </p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="pe0036">Lord B.</persName> has planted firs very
                    extensively on different spots properly dispersed all along the N. side of
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0104">
                        <hi rend="underline">Loch-Tay</hi>
                    </placeName>. He likewise gives the greatest encouragement for
                    inclosing the several farms by advancing money upon interest for that purpose.
                    Contrary to the accounts which you had by some mistake in the publick papers,
                    his tenants, though many of them have but small possessions and are poor, yet by
                    the good management under which the affairs of the country <unclear reason="illegible">are</unclear>, are the object of envy of many of their
                    neighbours ––––– </p>
                <p>This country is perhaps the most populous of the same extent in the Highlands of
                    Scotland — Upon the North side of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0104">
                        <hi rend="underline">Loch-tay</hi>
                    </placeName>, from <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0999">
                        <hi rend="underline">Finlarig</hi>
                    </placeName> to
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1004">the point of <hi rend="underline">Lyon</hi>
                    </placeName> there are about 1700 souls ––––– </p>
                <p>Oats, bear, pease <add place="above">lint</add> and potatoes are the only Crops
                    commonly sown in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">
                        <hi rend="underline">Breadalbane</hi>
                    </placeName>. The greatest return of oats is from four
                    to six grains for each grain sown, at an average but three or three and a half.
                    The greatest produce of <hi rend="underline">bear</hi> is from eight to ten, at
                    an average six. — When premiums were given a few years ago for the greatest
                    crops of lint, <persName ref="pe0312">Achalader</persName> informs me
                    that there were sown in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">Breadalbane</placeName>
                    from 70 to 120 hogsheads of Lintseed, each peck of which would at an average
                    yield two stone of drest flax; and when the linnen yarn, which is the great
                    staple commodity of this country, sold highest, there was no less than to the
                    value of 2000 £ of it exported in one year out of the Country. One of the
                    greatest losses therefore that the inhabitants at present sustain is the low
                    price of that commodity; the manufacture of which is so universally carried on
                    that there is commonly more flax imported every year than what grows in the
                    country.</p>
                <p> — There are great crops of potatoes reared by every person, the seed of which
                    has been often changed with advantage. The kind which is at present cultivated
                    most, and to best advantage is the <hi rend="underline">London-Lady</hi>, which
                    upon some farms yields at average about ten bolls for each that is planted. The
                    usual produce however among the common tenants is not above seven or eight fold
                    — One or two families have fallen upon the art of extracting from the root a
                    very strong and agreeable spirit, which turns out to be much cheaper than what
                    is distilled from any kind of grain. Very good <hi rend="underline">starch</hi>
                    is likewise made of it, which not only serves very well for dressing linnen, but
                    it also found to answer in the oven in some instances as well as
                        <sic>wheat-flower</sic> ––––– </p>
                <p>For two years past very considerable quantities of the <hi rend="underline">Lichen omphalodes</hi>, called in the Galic lang. <hi rend="underline">Corcar</hi>, have been exported from this and all the neighbouring
                    countries for the purposes of <hi rend="underline">dying</hi>, and sold from a
                    shilling to sixteen pence p<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> stone ––––– </p>
                <p>Great quantities of wool are now likewise exported —</p>
                <p>The best <add place="above">fat</add> weathers reared in the country and exported
                    from it, sell at about eleven shillings each; but small sheep of the old breed
                    sell only at about 6 shillings each ––––– </p>
                <p>The best parcels of black Cattle reared by some of the Gentlemen in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">
                        <hi rend="underline">Breadalbane</hi>
                    </placeName> have
                    been sold at five guineas each but the black Cattle commonly reared in the
                    country, sell at an average only at 2 £ 5 shillings each, when four years of
                    age––––– </p>
                <p>
                    <unclear reason="illegible">A Few</unclear> horses are reared ––––– </p>
                <p>These animals are in this and in many other parts of the Highlands seized with a
                    very extraordinary kind of distemper, when they happen to feed upon the tops of
                    the higher hills in the months of July and Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>,
                    which if no remedy is applyed proves fatal to them in less than 24 hours. The
                    common opinion of the natives is that it is owing to an animal like a weesel,
                    which some pretend to have seen, and which they imagine pours it's venom in
                    great quantities upon the grass. <unclear reason="illegible">It</unclear> is a
                    more probable conjecture however that the quality of the pasture must be the
                    cause of it. Pontoppidan speaks of a similar disease, if I remember well in
                        <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0538">his account of
                            Norway</title>
                    </bibl>, which he ascribes to the effects of a certain
                    plant: — In the event however that this distemper proceeds from feeding on one
                    of the <add place="above">Alpine</add> plants which grow upon the tops of our
                    higher hills, it is remarkable that no other species of animals are hurt by that
                    pasture but horses, and even they only in a certain season of the year, and more
                    commonly <add place="above">then</add> after a fall of rain, or before dew rises
                    from the grass in the morning —</p>
                <p>A universal swelling over the body is the great symptom of this disorder and,
                    when taken in time, a cure seldom fails to be effected by exercise, chaffing or
                    any means for promoting the discharge of sweat and urine, if persisted in for
                    some hours — The animal which is believed to do all this hurt is called by
                    different names in different parts of the Highlands, &amp; is probably the same
                    with the <hi rend="underline">Lavellan</hi> of <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0499">
                            <hi rend="underline">Sibbald</hi>
                        </title>
                    </bibl>.
                    The accounts at least we have of both are, I dare say, fabulous––––– </p>
                <p>Though this country is as much a grain or a Cattle country, yet it is so populous
                    that there is commonly every year some meal imported — none exported –––––</p>
                <p>Goats are banished for the sake of the woods —</p>
                <p>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">Breadalbane</placeName>
                </p>
                <p>The principal <add place="above">native</add> woods in this country are of Oak,
                    Ash, Birch, and Hazel. There were once likewise some natural woods of the <hi rend="underline">Pinus sylvestris</hi>, which are now almost extinct.
                    Different species of planted trees thrive here extremely well, particularly in
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0999">
                        <hi rend="underline">Finlarig</hi>
                    </placeName> —</p>
                <p>Salmon are found clean and fresh in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0104v">Loch-tay</placeName> on every day of the year, if search is made for them —
                    The only other fishes known to be in this lake are Pike, trout, Red Charre,
                    Perch, Lamprey, Eel, Bull-trout, parr, and minnow.</p>
                <p> — In some of the small lakes in the hills there are likewise plenty of excellent
                    trouts, and in one of them some pikes are found —</p>
                <p>The wild quadrupeds of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">
                        <hi rend="underline">Breadalbane</hi>
                    </placeName> are 1. Red Deer. The only forest in this
                    country where this animal now remains belongs to <persName ref="pe0036">Lord B.,</persName> and lies at the W. end of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1005">
                        <hi rend="underline">Glenlochy</hi>
                    </placeName>. It is
                    called that of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1006">
                        <hi rend="underline">Mam-Lorn</hi>
                    </placeName>, and by the common inhabitants <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1006">
                        <hi rend="underline">Corry-cheïch</hi>
                    </placeName>
                    i.e. the bason of mist. When the females are in season, the males are frequently
                    observed to fight bitterly; running against one another with a race, as rams do.
                    At every other time they seem to have an aversion to the Does and their young,
                    and keep always by themselves.</p>
                <p>Eagles and foxes are very destructive to their young, but dare not approach when
                    the dam is in sight. They arrive at their full size and growth at five years of
                    age. After that period their horns become every year smaller and rougher, but
                    continue to the same length. They cast them as they do their hair regularly once
                    a year. They go always against the wind, so that by it's direction their Keeper
                    knows exactly where at any time to find them. They have the senses of smelling
                    and seeing, and hearing excessively acute. The male however is not so very
                    quick-sighted as the female, on account of the grossness of it's horns. They
                    have an aversion at feeding with sheep and black Cattle, but not so much with
                    horses and goats, which in some forests are permitted to pasture along with
                    them.</p>
                <p>The severity of winter and spring often proves fatal to them. ––––– </p>
                <p>2. Roe. This animal is now very rare in this country, but abounds at present in
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0105">the neighbouring valley of
                        Glenlyon</placeName>, as for some years past <persName ref="pe0468">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Menzies of <hi rend="underline">Culdars</hi>
                    </persName> has paid great attention to it's preservation
                    ––––– </p>
                <p>3. Alpine hare. 4. Common hare. 5 Fox. 6. Badger. 7. Polecat. 8. Wild-Cat. 9.
                    Weesel. 10. Ermin. 11. Martin. This animal is exceedingly rare in this country.
                    One of them was killed some years ago upon <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0815">
                        <hi rend="underline">Ben-more</hi>
                    </placeName>, but I cannot learn with
                    certainty whether it was the <hi rend="underline">white</hi> or <hi rend="underline">yellow-breasted Martin</hi>. I have lately got the stuft
                    skin of one that was killed in one of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0751">the old
                        birch-woods of Rannoch</placeName>, which was the <hi rend="underline">yellow-breasted</hi>, and I suppose the only species in that country. — 12.
                    The Rat. none of the great <hi rend="underline">Norway rats</hi> have as yet
                    penetrated into this country. 13. The Mouse. 14. The short-tailed field-mouse. I
                    have found this animal high up in one of the hills of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl1007">
                        <hi rend="underline">Glen-creran</hi>
                    </placeName> and
                    of this country. It feeds in harvest upon the ripe seeds of some of the coarse
                    grasses, as appeared upon opening the stomach of one which was killed in that
                    season. 14. The Shrew-mouse. 15. Water Shrew-mouse. 16. The Mole. 17. The
                    Hedge-hog. 18. <hi rend="underline">The Otter</hi>. An opinion prevails in the
                    Highlands that this species of animals have a King or Leader, which is rarely to
                    be met with, and is always attended with a number of common otters.</p>
                <p>They describe it as of a greater size than the common, and sometimes variegated
                    with white spots. They believe that it is never killed without the sudden death
                    of a man or some other animal at the same time, and ascribe the most
                    extraordinary virtues to it's Skin. The least portion of it they think would
                    render the warrior almost invulnerable, preserve the house in which it is lodged
                    from the infection of diseases, and insure his vessel to the mariner amidst the
                    severest storms.</p>
                <p> — What might have at first given occasion to all this fabulous account, it is
                    hard to say. It is a certain fact however that a few years ago an <add place="above">accidental</add> variety of this animal, with a number of
                    round white spots upon it's back, such as they describe, has been killed in the
                    neighbourhood of this country. I have had a description of it from the Furrier
                    who brought it, and from others who saw it. —</p>
                <p>19. The Bat –––––</p>
                <p>It is extraordinary that though <hi rend="underline">vipers</hi> are found in
                    great numbers in the countries lying both north and South of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">
                        <hi rend="underline">Breadalbane</hi>
                    </placeName> yet
                    here they are hardly ever seen. <hi rend="underline">Frogs</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">Lizards</hi>, both the <hi rend="underline">nimble</hi> and
                        <hi rend="underline">brown</hi>, are common here ––––– </p>
                <p>The birds of this country are 1. The <hi rend="underline">Ring-tailed Eagle</hi>.
                    2 Sea-Eagle. 3. Osprey. —</p>
                <p>4. Kite. 5. Common Buzzard. 6. Hen-Harrier 7. Kestrell. 8. Hobby. 9. Merlin. 10.
                    Wite Owl. 11. Brown Owl. 12 Raven. 13. Crow. 14. Rook 15. Hooded Crow. This bird
                    breeds in this country and never migrates out of it ––––– </p>
                <p>16. Magpy. 17 Jay. 18. Jack-daw. 19. Greater Spotted woodpecker. 20. Cuckoo. 21.
                    Nuthatch. 22. Creeper. 23. Cornish Chough. 24 Black Cock. 25 Grous. 26.
                    Tarmachan. 27 Partridge. 28. Ringdove 29. Fieldfare. 30. Throstle. 31. Redwing.
                    32. Blackbird. 33. Ring-ouzel 34. Water-Ouzel. 35. Sky-Lark. 36. Tit-Lark. 37.
                    House swallow. 38 Martin. 39 Sand Martin 40. Swift. 41 Goatsucker. 42 Red-start.
                    43. Red-Breast. 44 Fly-catcher. 45 Hedge sparrow. 46. Willow-wren. 47
                    Golden-crested wren. — 48 Wren. 49. Wheat-Ear. 50. Whin-Chat. 51 White Throat.
                    52. White Water Wagtail — 53. Yellow Water Wagtail. 54 Bull-Finch 55. Sparrow.
                    56. Green-Finch. 57. Gold-Finch. 58. Chaffinch. 59. Brambling — 60. Linnet. 61.
                    Red-headed Linnet — 62. Lesser red-headed Linnet. 63. Mountain Linnet. 64.
                    Bunting. 65 Yellow-Hammer. 66. Reed Sparrow. 67. Greater Brambling. I imagine
                    our <hi rend="underline">Snow-flake</hi> must be the same with this bird. I have
                    had three or four fresh specimens of it, each of which answered to your
                    description in the <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0026">B.Z.</title>
                    </bibl>, nor could I find that there was any material
                    difference in the Hind-Claw or otherwise. 68. Great Titmouse. 69. Blue Titmouse.
                    70 Colemouse. 71. Long-tailed Titmouse. 72. The Heron. 73. Wood-Cock — 74.
                    Snipe. 75. Jack Snipe. 76. Lapwing — 77. Sand-Piper. 78. Green Plover. 79.
                    Dottrel. 80 Water-Rail. 81. Land-Rail. 82. Little Grebe. 83. Common Gull. 84 Red
                    headed Goosander — 85 Wild Swan. 86. Scaup-Duck. 87. Golden-Eye. 88.
                    Shield-Drake. 89. Wild Duck. 90. Teal</p>
                <p>Besides these, of the greatest part of which I have had fresh specimens, one of
                    the <hi rend="underline">Divers</hi>, I suppose the same with that on <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0814">
                        <hi rend="underline">Loch-Rannoch</hi>
                    </placeName>,
                    has been killed some years ago in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">
                        <hi rend="underline">Breadalbane</hi>
                    </placeName>. The <hi rend="underline">Black Guillemot</hi> and one of the <hi rend="underline">Red-shanks</hi>
                    have likewise been found <del rend="overstrike">found</del> here. And a few
                    others, I dare say, may have still escaped observation. ––––– Upon the whole
                    however the foregoing List, with the addition of the <hi rend="underline">Green
                        Wood-Pecker</hi>, <hi rend="underline">Cross-Bill</hi>, the <hi rend="underline">Wood Lark</hi>
                    <add place="above">and a few others,</add> may, as far as I know, be considered
                    as comprehending the principal birds not only in this country, but in the
                    greatest part of the inland Highlands. –––––</p>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. Our seasons in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0813">Breadalbane</placeName>
                        are not nearly so moist as upon the W. Coast. Here however, as well as
                        there, the greatest rains are carried to us by S.W. winds from the Atlantick
                        —</p>
                    <p>Upon some of our higher mountains spots of snow often continue all summer
                        undissolved —</p>
                    <p>Towards the end of Oct<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> sometimes a thick heavy
                        white mist moves slowly from the East, and covers all the vallies and lower
                        grounds with universal darkness. It rises only to a certain height in the
                        atmosphere; and I have once or twice had the pleasure of ascending above it
                        to the top of some of our high hills. There the sky was perfectly serene,
                        and the sun shone with great brightness. The prospect afforded on all hands
                        was the most picturesque one could well imagine, a boundless Ocean of
                        shining Mist, with the green tops of mountains rising every where out it,
                        like so many round islands, shaped mostly like a sugar-loaf — I had at the
                        same time the opportunity of attending to another phænomenon. When drawing
                        at any time near the mist on the North side of the hill, my shadow fell upon
                        it, the head, but no other part, appeared encircled with rays, forming at
                        the same time a bright round rainbow –––––</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>