<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0434">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>John Stuart to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP369</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>13</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    <date when="1798-08-29"/>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0277">Mountstuart</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>

            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0616">Mountstuart</placeName> 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Aug<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 1790</dateline>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>While here upon a visit to <persName ref="pe0278">the Marquiss of
                        Bute</persName>, I embrace the opportunity of dropping you a few lines
                    franked by <persName ref="pe0278">his Lordship</persName> —</p>
                <p>I now beg leave to return you many thanks for the entertainment I received from
                    the perusal of your ingenious <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0034">Account of the Parishes of <sic>Holywood</sic>
                            &amp;c</title>
                    </bibl>, an Account which to me is the more entertaining,
                    that it contains a particular description of the Family and Place of <persName ref="pe0232">a Gentleman</persName>, whose acquaintance and
                    friendship I have now been so long honoured with, and whose welfare &amp;
                    prosperity I will always rejoice at. My friend <persName ref="pe0158">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Intyre,</persName> the Minister of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0213">Glenorchay</placeName>, has likewise had the perusal of <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0034">the book</title>
                    </bibl>, for
                    which he desires I will return you his best thanks. He is at present in good
                    health. But in December last he met with one or two of those severe tryals, from
                    which in this world even the best men are not often exempted. About two or three
                    weeks after receiving the accounts of the death of a very promising young man, a
                    son of his, in <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0704">the West Indies</placeName>,
                        <persName ref="pe0469">M<hi rend="superscript">rs.</hi> M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Intyre</persName>, who upon the forenoon of the
                        25<hi rend="superscript">th.</hi> day of said month paid a visit along with
                    him to a Family in the neighbourhood, seemingly in her usual health, in the
                    evening retired to her room, where not long after she was found by her Family
                    upon her knees, and in a swoon. Every effort was used to recover, but without
                    effect. She expired immediately without a sigh or a groan ––––– When you was
                    here in 1772, I remember you was much pleased with this place. It is now still a
                    finer place than it was then, the plantations having grown so considerably since
                    that time, and the present <persName ref="pe0278">Lord Bute</persName>
                    having with much taste improved it in many respects. I will always recollect,
                    with pleasure, the happy hours I spent with you here that year, and in the other
                    islands and places you visited. But it is with pain I reflect that our worthy
                    and ingenious friend <persName ref="pe0139">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Lightfoot</persName>, whose memory will always be dear to me,
                    is no more.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am, with great esteem <lb/>Dear Sir, <lb/>Your most obliged and
                        <lb/>humble Servant</salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0023">John Stuart</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>