<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct0542">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>George Paton to Thomas Pennant</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Warwick</settlement>
                        <repository>Warwickshire County Record Office</repository>
                        <idno>CR2017/TP326</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>13</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0228">George Paton</persName>
                    <date when="1790-03-04"/>
                    <placeName ref="pl0696">Custom House Edinburgh</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <placeName ref="pl0734">Bruton Street London</placeName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>The <sic>vicessitudes</sic> of Life are many, &amp; those come upon Mankind
                    unexpectedly, which require the exercise of Christian fortitude in the strongest
                    degree: — I am sorry to learn that you have lost so many Friends, heartily do I
                    wish this may be supplied by the comfortable enjoyment of your Family, especialy
                    when engaged so laudably in the acquisition of Knowledge: may <persName ref="pe0236">your Son's</persName> Visit abroad be prosperous &amp; his
                    Return to <placeName ref="pl0777">Britain</placeName> again be safe. — From a
                    Paper lately fallen into my hands, written by my Father I cannot look for the
                    length of my days now, as it assures me to have past more years than I thought
                    i.e since July 1721, but to drop this topick at the time, — let us pass our
                    Lives as we ought to do.</p>
                <p>I am glad that the short hints on the Salt were of any Service to you, return
                    thanks for the Specimen of your Labour, with what you may be pleased to oblige the World <del rend="overstrike">with</del> I shall be always happy to peruse &amp; assign
                    a carefull corner in my small Collection.</p>
                <p>
                    <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bi0304">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                            <hi rend="underline">Smellie's Philosophy of Natural
                            History</hi>
                        </title>
                    </bibl> was published t'other day, an Acquaintance
                    passing to <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> now on the way I am
                    hopefull that you will find two Copies, shortly hence, at <persName ref="pe0026">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> White's Bookseller</persName> for your
                    Acceptance from me, having ordered the Parcel to be left there to meet you while
                    residing in <placeName ref="pl0699">London</placeName> expecting this will reach
                    you in due time.</p>
                <p>You have inclosed <rs type="art" ref="ar0087">Kay's Sketch of Cap<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Grose</rs>, hope he will soon begin his Tour
                    in our Western Regions,<note type="editorial">The antiquarian Francis Grose made
                        tours of Scotland in 1788, 1789 and 1790, in order to gather materials for
                        his <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bi0243">
                                <hi rend="italic">Antiquities
                                    of Scotland</hi>
                            </title>
                        </bibl>, published 1789-1791.</note> if
                    you chance to see him, my best Compliments wait of him, I do hear that the
                        <placeName ref="pl1178">
                        <hi rend="underline">old Tower house of
                        Udny</hi>
                    </placeName> in <placeName ref="pl0732">Aberdeenshire</placeName>
                    is well worthy of his inspection, the plan of this building being of a singular
                    kind: <rs type="art" ref="ar0088">a draft of it</rs> was made by <persName ref="pe0001">Doctor Anderson</persName>, if he has a Copy thereof, I shall
                    solicit a Sketch of it for you from him. — <persName ref="pe0001">The
                        Doctor</persName> some days ago exprest his warmest returns for the
                    Civilities you shewed him while you was in the north of <placeName ref="pl0705">this Country</placeName>, his Letter to me with his M.S Plan I inclose for
                    your perusal &amp; if <persName ref="pe0236">your Son</persName> can procure the
                    Literary Countenance of any qualified Person in the Course of his Travels, this
                    would be a very high piece of merit to <persName ref="pe0001">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Anderson</persName> to gain their
                    Correspondence, such a plan as he <sic>pourposes</sic> will be of real Service
                    to the world: — when his proposals are printed I shall be sure to lend you some
                    of them, the inclosed is handed for your recomendation of its contents for
                        <sic>your's</sic> notice if deserving it.<note type="editorial">The proposal
                        and manuscript plan Paton refers to likey relate to James Anderson's
                        attempts to gather support for his periodical project, <bibl type="editorial">
                            <title ref="bi0138">
                                <hi rend="italic">The Bee, or
                                    Literary Weekly Intelligencer</hi>
                            </title>
                        </bibl> (1791-1794), a
                            <bibl type="authorial">
                            <title ref="bi0581">
                                <hi rend="italic">Prospectus</hi>
                            </title>
                        </bibl> for which was printed in
                        1790.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName ref="pe0049">M<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Cardonnel</persName>
                    desired me to present his best Compliments with gratefull thanks for <rs type="art" ref="ar0089">the Drafts</rs> he received from you by <persName ref="pe0105">Cap<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Grose</persName>. — I've
                    added <rs type="art" ref="ar0090">a portrait of a remarkable Man at
                        Dunfermline</rs>, he is an adept in the Hebrew &amp;<hi rend="superscript">c.</hi> &amp; other Eastern Languages from some peculiarity has refrained
                    the shaving or cutting his Beards, have seen him walking thro' our Streets, but
                    the young Boys now restrain their following after him as an uncommon person; he
                    was educated to have been a Clergyman: <persName ref="pe0068">D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Lort</persName> when here was much pleased
                        <gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" atLeast="1" atMost="4"/> that Portrait,
                    it is very like him.<note type="editorial">Several portraits of Lort are known
                        to have been made. Paton may be referring to <rs type="art" ref="ar0091">John Downman's 1777 portrait</rs>, or <rs type="art" ref="ar0092">Francis Grose's more recent caricature of Lort, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Antiquarian Mastiff</hi>
                        </rs>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I am sincerely <lb/>D<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi> Sir <lb/>Your
                        most obed<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi> Serv<hi rend="superscript">t.</hi>
                    </salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="pe0228">GPaton</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName ref="pl0696">Custom h<hi rend="superscript">o.</hi> Edinb<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                    </placeName>
                    <lb/>4 March 1790}</dateline>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Thomas Pennant Esq<hi rend="superscript">r.</hi>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Bruton Street</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>London</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>