<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="CT.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ct1008">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Thomas Pennant to Richard Bull</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <settlement>Aberystwyth</settlement>
                        <repository>National Library of Wales</repository>
                        <idno>5500C</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                        <ab>
                            <locus>no. 8</locus>
                        </ab>
                    </msContents>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName ref="pe0232">Thomas Pennant</persName>
                    <date when="1780-09-08"/>
                    <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName ref="pe0313">Richard Bull</persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0001">Downing</placeName>
                        <choice>
                            <abbr>Aug.</abbr>
                            <expan>August</expan>
                        </choice> 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. 1780.</dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>I sent for <persName ref="pe0324">Ingleby</persName> on the
                        <sic>receit</sic> of your favor. he assures me that <choice>
                        <abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan>your</expan>
                    </choice>
                    <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0012">Book</title>
                    </bibl>
                   <note type="editorial">This appears to refer to Bull's copy of Pennant's A tour
                        in Wales. MDCCLXX (1778). See discussion in NLW 5500C, no. 7. LINK TO WORKS
                        LIST: Thomas Pennant, A tour in Wales. MDCCLXX (London: Henry Hughes, 1778):
                        Bull's copy</note> shall be finished by the day you wish. If no public
                    calamity happens, I hope to put <bibl type="authorial">
                        <title ref="bidb.xml#bi0013">my second &amp; last part of the welsh
                        tour</title>
                    </bibl>.<note type="editorial">A Journey to Snowdon (London: Henry
                        Hughes: 1781): generic. This was not in fact the final volume of Pennant's
                        Welsh tours.</note> in the press in october. a copy on large paper will beg <choice>
                        <abbr>y<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan>your</expan>
                    </choice> acceptance.<note type="editorial">A Journey to Snowdon (London:
                        printed by Henry Hughes, 1781): Bull's copy [LP]</note> I mean that two on
                    that size shall be sent as every six sheets are worked off: &amp; <persName ref="pe0324">Ingleby</persName> if you desire, shall instantly copy
                    all the marginal <del>e</del>
                    <sic>aditions</sic>, <persName ref="pe0014">Moses</persName> puts on my
                    copy<note type="editorial">A Journey to Snowdon (London: printed by Henry
                        Hughes, 1781): TP's copy [LP]</note>
                </p>
                <p>In respect to <persName ref="pe0327">Robson</persName> he was very
                    faulty in not seeing the catch word V. at the bottom of the <choice>
                        <abbr>p.</abbr>
                        <expan>page</expan>
                    </choice> in my swiss views;<note type="editorial">There is no trace of a
                        publication directly on Switzerland by Pennant and no manuscript compilation
                        has been identified either. The 'swiss views' discussed here is clearly a
                        printed work (vide Robson's involvement and the reference to 'the letter
                        press of the swiss views' in no. 9). Pennant may be referring to a personal
                        copy of a work by another, clearly with a strong visual element. The
                        evidence of two drawings labelled in pencil as the work of 'T Pennant' and
                        which appear to be related to the latter's travels in Switzerland should
                        also be considered. The drawings in question are included in Pennant's
                        extra-illustrated manuscript copy of his Literary life (NLW 12706E). One of
                        them is a print and it seems possible that it formed part of a publication
                        on Switzerland by Pennant himself. As a gentleman, Pennant would have been
                        wary of circulating his own drawings in print, and this may account for the
                        disappearance of this publication from public view and from the public
                        record.</note> but I hope he will be honest enough to do me justice &amp;
                    that I shall not suffer for his neglect. I had heard many complaints since
                        <persName ref="pe0328">Faulder</persName> left him of having only
                    raw lads in his shops, which will certainly injure him. As I have sent the book
                    back, I shall be extremely obliged to you for watching the arrival of the second
                    part of the description. It must now be new bound in two. viz. the plates in one
                    &amp; description in the other. If you give yourself the trouble of calling at
                        <persName ref="pe0327">Robsons</persName> next week you will see
                    what a fine book it was. I admire it much for the great fidelity of the views in
                    all parts of <placeName ref="pldb.xml#pl0791">Swisserland</placeName> which I
                    visited.</p>
                <p>I am most extremely sensible of your friendship but will not trespass on it too
                    far. I may perhaps trouble you once more about the binding of the book<note type="editorial">Referring once again to 'swiss views'.</note> which has
                    plagued me so much.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I remain <lb/>with true regard <lb/>Dear Sir <lb/>your obliged &amp; most <lb/>
                        <choice>
                        <abbr>obed<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Serv<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                            </abbr>
                        <expan>obedient Servant</expan>
                    </choice>
                    </salute>
                    <signed>
                        <persName ref="bidb.xml#bi0012">
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Tho.</abbr>
                                <expan>Thomas</expan>
                            </choice> Pennant</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>